Hello everyone. My name is Dr. Raj
Gandekar. I graduated with a PhD in
machine learning from the Massachusetts
Institute of Technology and I'm one of
the three co-founders of Vijuara AI
Labs. Today I'm incredibly excited to
present this video to you in which we
are going to build a small language
model fully from scratch. I've been
working on this video for the past 5 to
6 months and I'm truly excited right now
to assemble all of it together and
present it to all of you. Like we do in
all of our videos, we'll be showing you
everything from the nuts and bolts. I'll
not assume anything. I'll show you each
and every calculation, each and every
mathematical detail on the whiteboard
and then we'll also do coding. Towards
the end, we'll build a fully functional
small language model which gives good
quality responses. So let's get
[Music]
started. All right. So let's get started
on this journey. Today our main goal is
that we are going to build a small
language model fully from
scratch. Let me first show you what we
are going to build today. Here is the
Google collab code file which we are
going to run fully. I'll walk you
through each and every line of code over
here and towards the end as you can see
over here we are going to give uh a
sample sentence and we are going to
generate certain stories out of
it and I'm I'll make sure that the
response of the
um LLM or the response of the small
language model which we build is good
quality responses. So you can think of
this tutorial as a bit of a production
level tutorial because I'll also teach
you some things which we usually need to
do to accelerate the training process.
Some things which we usually need to do
so that computations become memory uh
memory efficient
etc. So this is not just a toy project
which we'll be assembling and the
results which you get towards the end
are do not make sense. But as you will
see the sentences which our small
language model can generate actually
start to make a lot of
sense. Okay. So this is what our goal is
from this tutorial video. First let me
clarify to all of you what does a small
language model actually mean. So if you
look at language modeling itself, models
just keep on getting larger and larger
and larger. Right? GPT4 if you see over
here was
about 1 trillion parameters although
it's not public information yet. GPT3
the largest model was around 175 billion
parameters. And there's the scaling law
which says that as the number of
parameters increase the performance of
the language model increases
proportionately. So researchers went on
increasing the size of language models
to get better and better performance out
of them. However, people soon realize
that what if let's say if there's a huge
architecture for the language model
which let me show here by this circle
right and this huge architecture gets
the job done it produces coherent
responses what if I can get similar
responses but with a smaller size
language model what if I reduce the
number of parameters to not as large as
1 trillion or 175 billion but what if I
can take it down to a million parameters
or a few million parameters. Can my
model still do the task well or instead
of a million what if first we try a few
billion and see if the model does the
task
well. So if you see over here here I
have presented some models which work
relatively well and their sizes you can
see here start from around 94 million
340 million 1.5 million etc. In this
figure also you can see the Quen 2.5
billion model, the Quen 1.5 billion
model, they perform very well and their
size if you see 1.5 billion is about 100
times lesser than 175 billion right
which is GPT3 size and it's about a,000
times lesser than GPT4 size and still
they perform relatively well. The appeal
of small language models is that as the
model sites get smaller, of course, it's
more easier to run, it's more faster to
implement. And if you connect the
development of language models and apply
it into production, you of course want
things which work fast. So similar to
the MOS law for the chip size, right?
And the chip size reduced exponentially
over time. I believe that the size of
language models is also going to come
down and within four to five years we
may reach a stage where all of us will
have a language model downloaded locally
on our mobiles which we can interact
with. This whole field of trying to
reduce the size of language models
essentially and to retain their
performance is what's called small
language modeling. Now what is small
that's not clearly defined but anything
which is less than let's say 1 billion
for example would be considered a small
language model currently if you manage
to have something which is of the size
of 1 to 50 million that's awesome
because that's definitely a small
language
model so today we are going to build
such model
um and we are going to use a GPU but I'm
going to show you how you can get access
to that GPU etc but we are not going to
use a very very deeply computational
traditionally heavy architecture with a
reasonably light architecture we are
going to get good results when we
develop a small language model. So the
language model which we are going to
develop will have a size of around 15
million
parameters and that's why it's safe to
call it a small language
model. So if you take this into context
of GPT3 this is probably around uh 1,000
or 10 to 5 times lower than
uh GPT3 because that's 175 billion and
that's even around 10 to 6 or 10 to 7
times smaller than let's say GPT4 the
size of the model which we are going to
generate today. So that's the scale of
uh the model size we are going to
operate on in this tutorial. But you'll
be surprised to know that at the
specific task which we look at the model
does relatively well with this context
set. Let's get started. We are going to
divide this project into six parts.
First we are going to go through our
data set. Then we will do a bit of data
prep-processing. Then we will assemble
the entire model architecture.
Then we'll set up the training pipeline
of the small language model. Then we'll
pre-train the entire small language
model. And finally we'll do the
inference. Don't worry if these terms or
some of the terms I'm saying are not
making sense right now. I'll try to go
through everything in a lot of detail so
that you understand every single aspect
of this pipeline. These are the
whiteboard notes which I'll be referring
to throughout this project and the
Google collab note or the Google collab
code file which I've already shown you.
We'll be going through this code file
after we finish each and every part on
the
whiteboard. Okay. So with that let's get
started with the first part of this
project which is the data set which we
have. Every language modeling project
begins with your data set right and as
you might be knowing GPT3, GPT4 etc was
trained on billions and billions of data
set which we do not have right now or I
don't have access to this right now and
would have been very difficult to
condense all of this in this small
tutorial. So so I turned to a paper
which became very popular in 2023 and
this paper is called as tiny stories.
You can check the number of citations
which this paper
have. So you'll see that it has around
219 citations, right? And what this
paper tried to do, so they tried to
answer the question that how small can
language models be and still speak
coherent English. And their main claim
was
that small language models were not
working that well until the time this
paper was published. And their main
claim was that small language models are
trained on this entire data set which is
available all over the internet. Right?
But they said that what if we reduce the
size of this data set itself. What if we
reduce the size of the data set so that
the data set is for a specific task. So
this is called as a specific task data
set.
And suppose let's suppose that we very
intelligently curate this data set so
that it captures all the nuances of the
English
language. Can we now train a small
language model on this small data
set? Let me explain this further to you.
In fact, the way these researchers
constructed this data set is that they
basically looked at stories which would
be appropriate for 3 to four year old
kids.
They only looked at stories for 3 to
four year old kids and that's why they
called this data set as tiny stories.
They constructed this data set. The way
they constructed this data set is from
GPT4. So they asked GPT4 to construct a
huge amount of stories for 3 to four
year old kids. And the smartness or the
beauty of this approach is that this
will be a very small data set, right? It
won't why would we need all the
information of the world for this? We
only need stories for that age group. So
those will only contain a specific words
but they capture all the nuances of the
English language because the stories
have to be written in fluent English.
The grammar needs to be correct. So if
we are testing that can a language model
essentially learn from all these data
set and produce coherent
English then ideally this is a great
data set to have. So what is our goal
here? Our goal here is that can my
model or can my 15 million can my 15
million
model learn from this data
set? learn from this data set. And what
does it mean learning from the data set?
It actually means that my model should
be able to do two things. My model
should understand the form of the
English language. Sorry, my model should
understand let's say the structure or
the form of the English language which
means it should generate grammatically
correct sentences and second my model
should also understand something about
the meaning which means that my model
should be able to come up with stories
on its own which are suitable for 3 to
four year old kids and if we could
achieve this that would be truly
incredible right because just from this
small data set now I'm able to teach a
language model about the English
language
The model starts from no knowledge. It
has no information about language. It
has no information about the fact that
let's say
uh subject verb object that is the
structure followed in English language.
It does not know this. But can we teach
this? Can the model learn this from this
data set? And if we are able to
successfully create this model, which
means that if we are able to
successfully create a model which
outputs coherent English stories, we are
successful at our task of creating a
small language model. And what is small?
We are going to create only a 15 million
parameter model. Okay. So we are going
to work with the tiny stories data set.
This these researchers have made their
data set public. So we are going to use
this data set. If you scroll over to
this, this data set is also available on
hugging face. So you'll see that they
split the data set into two parts. They
split it into training and validation.
So even although I say this is a tiny
data set, it still has 2 million
rows. And uh every row of this data set
is a story meant for 3 to four year old
kids. So for example, if you see this
row, we see the first story, right? One
day a little girl named Lily found a
needle in her room. She knew it was
difficult to play with it because it was
sharp. Lily wanted to share the needle
with her mom etc etc. And this whole
story proceeds like this. Remember these
stories have been generated from GPT4
but they constitute our data set like
that. This is one story. Similarly, we
have 2 million stories like this which
are in our training data set and about
20,000 stories in our testing data set.
So, we are going to work with this data.
As I mentioned at the start of this
video, this is not going to be a toy
project video, but we are actually going
to work with real data sets over here.
Okay. So, this is the data set and we'll
use this data set which is specifically
meant for 3 to four year old kids. This
will help us reduce the size of our
language model because now I'm not
assembling all the data from all over
the internet. I'm looking at a specific
corpus of data meant for 3 to four year
old kids. And the question is that can
we construct can we construct a language
model with just 10 to 15 million
parameters and which produces coherent
text. And if you think about this sounds
like an incredibly difficult problem,
right? Because you have to teach a model
something about language otherwise how
can the model come up with stories. We
want the model to produce coherent
stories towards the end of this. We want
the model to produce stories which make
sense on its own. So it's like imagine
an alien coming to the earth and you
want the alien to speak English. So
instead of loading the alien with all
the information available on Wikipedia,
on Google, everywhere, you just give the
alien stories for 3 to four year old
because through those stories also the
alien can learn the English language and
then you feed all this data to the alien
and then you hope that the alien will
learn everything and come up with
coherent stories on his or her own.
So this sounds like a challenging
problem but that's what's so exciting
about this project. Okay. So now I'm
going to go to Google Collab and we are
going to just start executing some code
blocks as we uh finish understanding the
steps on the whiteboard. So the part one
is loading our data set. So I go over
here and here you can see that you can
um this data set is present on hugging
face right. So you have to first install
data sets uh which is a package through
which you can load any data set on
hugging phase. So you can run this
command and it will take some time to
install this. It took about 30 seconds
on mine. Okay. After this point you have
to import the load data set function and
here you have to pass the URL of the uh
here you have to pass the URL of your
data set on hugging face. So if I go to
hugging face right now, you'll see that
this is the URL, right? Uh this is the
URL which I have marked over here and
that's the URL which I'm passing over
here. So load data set and this URL. And
when you run this, you'll see that the
data set has been loaded now
fully. And we see that the since the
data had two parts already, right? We
had a training data and validation data.
We have two types of data which have
already been loaded. The train split and
the validation split. validation split.
Okay. So the data set has fully been
loaded. Now this loading of the data set
might take some time for you because
remember we are loading 2 million rows,
right? We are loading 2 million stories
in our training data. Um so as you can
see here we are 2 million stories in our
training data and we have about 20,000
stories in our validation data. So this
does take some time but once this is
done your data set is successfully
loaded. One more thing which I want to
mention right at the start is that I'm
changing the runtime here to T uh A100
GPU. So now if you are on the Google
Collab free tire you can do T4 GPU but
the training will take a huge amount of
time on T4 GPU. You can run it overnight
for 8 to 10 hours and then it will be
complete. But if you switch to Google
Collab Pro which is just $10 per month,
you can run the training with an A100
GPU or the L4 GPU. Both are very strong
and the training roughly takes just 25
to 30 minutes on an A100 GPU. But if you
have a T4 GPU, it might easily take
around 6 to 7 hours. It can be run on a
free tire also. So no problem if you
just have a T4 GPU. But keep in mind
that it might take some time. And never
run this code on CPU because it will
fail. You will not be able to run this
code on CPU. So it should be either of
these GPUs which is provided by Google
Collab. Okay. So let's go to the
whiteboard. Right now the step one is
done where we have loaded our data set.
I hope until this point all of you have
understood the aim here. Our data set is
only stories understood by 3 to four
year old kids. We are going to use this
data set to teach our language model
about the English language. So that
ultimately it produces stories which
look like the ones in the data set.
Okay, that's going to be the purpose of
our small language model. Now let's move
to part two which is data
prep-processing. All right. So data
prep-processing is one of the most
important parts of essentially training
a large language model. And let me show
you the whole training pipeline
actually. So if you look at the pipeline
of training a large language model,
usually we have three blocks, right? We
have the input block which I've shown
over here. We have the processor block
which I've marked over here and then we
have the output block. We are going to
assemble all three blocks today. But
just keep in mind that in literature and
even in uh everywhere everyone talks
about the processor block because that's
where cool stuff is happening. But input
block does not receive that much
attention although this is one of the
most important steps. Here is where the
data data processing actually happens
for the input text which we have and uh
that's why I'm going to go into a fair
amount of detail for this part because
without understanding how the data is
processed in the input block you won't
understand what happens to the data when
it enters the processor or what happens
to the data when it enters the
transformer block. Okay. So let's
understand data prep-processing. So
remember first that LLMs or essentially
computer for that matter it cannot
understand sentences right. It cannot
understand sentences. It cannot
understand text or words like humans
do. It only understands numerical. It
only understands numerical data.
So what we have to do is that somehow we
have to take our input data which has
been present over here and we have to
convert it into a numerical
format. Now think about how would you
actually do this right? Let's say let me
take this story over here. Let me take a
screenshot. And if you understand how
this is done for one story, we'll of
course understand how it can be done for
all the stories. Right? So I've taken a
screenshot over here and I want us to
think how will you convert this entire
paragraph into
numbers. So the first thing which might
come to your mind is that I'll do uh
every word will be assigned some number.
So I'll divide this paragraph into bunch
of words and then I'll assign every word
a number. Or the second thing which
might come to your mind is that I'll
divide this paragraph into characters
and I'll assign every character a
number. The first type of method in
which every word is assigned a number is
called as word based
tokenization. And the second type of
method where every character is
essentially assigned a number or a token
that's called as character based
tokenization. Now it turns out that to
develop language models both of these
tokenization forms are not that
efficient. Why? Because when you have
character level
tokenization, every character is a
token. So the input text will be get
converted into a huge number of tokens
and our transformer block which is the
processor can only pay attention to a
certain number of tokens at a time. So
character based tokenization does not
work at all. Um second word based
tokenization right. So if every word is
essentially one token, the issue happens
when we have
uh let's say words where spelling
mistakes are there. If words have
spelling mistakes, they will not be
mapped to any token. That's the first
problem. And the second problem is that
whenever you do tokenization, you
maintain something called as the
vocabulary. You maintain something
called as the vocabulary. This
vocabulary consists of the list of
tokens and their corresponding token
ids. So if you do word based
tokenization, these tokens will be all
the words. And if you just look at the
English language itself, we have about
half a million or 500,000 words in the
English language itself. So in the case
of word based tokenization the
vocabulary size becomes very large and
that's a problem for us because
vocabulary size affects our computations
when we are going to predict the next
token in a large language
model. Usually the higher the vocabulary
size the longer the
computational the longer the
computational time and the higher is the
computational memory. So both of these
are tokenization methods which we don't
want. So then what's the best solution?
The best solution is something
intermediate and that's that
intermediate stage is called as subword
tokenization. That intermediate stage is
called subword tokenization. In subword
tokenization what we do is that we
maintain a vocabulary of
tokens which can be characters which can
be words and which can also be subwords.
So words which are not very commonly
occurring right like for example
tokenization for example it is usually
split into two words isation so
isization becomes one subword that
becomes a separate token and this token
becomes another token so in token in
subword based tokenization what we do is
that characters are of course retained
as individual tokens that much is fine
all commonly occurring words are
retained as tokens but all the words
which are not that common they are
broken down into subwords
This solves our vocabulary issue because
every word is now not a separate token.
Some words can be broken down into
subwords and this also solves the
character based tokenization issue which
breaks the text into huge number of
tokens. So subword tokenization is that
optimal scheme. So usually what is done
in subboard tokenization is that there
is an algorithm which is called as the
bite pair encoding
algorithm. Bite pair encoding algorithm
and that's also called BPE. This is an
algorithm which takes in a data set.
This algorithm takes in a data set and
it gives us the subwords or it gives us
the list of tokens which the data set
needs to be converted
into. Right? And these tokens as I
mentioned can be characters, these can
be words or these can be subwords. All
three are possible. Essentially what
bite pair encoding does is that it just
merges the commonly occurring bytes
together until you reach a prescribed
vocabulary size. I'm not going into too
many details of bite pair encoding here
for the purposes of this tutorial. It's
okay if you have a higher level
understanding of what is exactly done in
bite pair encoding. So what now we are
going to do is that we are going to feed
our entire data set into this bite pair
encoding model and this is also called
as the tokenizer. So the tokenizer what
the tokenizer does is that the tokenizer
takes our data
set. The tokenizer takes our data
set and then it converts it into a bunch
of
tokens. These tokens are each individual
units and then every token will
essentially be assigned a token
ID. That's this whole process which
needs to happen at the start before a
data is fed to the transformer block.
There are many other steps also but the
first thing is you take the data set and
then what you do is that you convert the
data set into uh essentially a bunch of
tokens and then you assign the tok each
token a token ID and the way the data
sets are converted into a bunch of
tokens is through the tokenizer. Now we
are going to use a tokenizer used by
GPT2 which is the same as what I had
mentioned earlier that's the bite pair
encoding. Okay. And we are going to pass
all of our stories over here as the data
set. We are going to pass all of our
stories over here. But instead of uh
just passing every story and converting
it into a bunch of tokens, there is uh
uh there is
a common way or there is a better way to
do this which is good in terms of uh
computational efficiency. And for this I
have borrowed this part of the logic
from Andre Karpati's nano GPT. This can
be a good time to mention that Andre
Karpath's nano GPT code has inspired a
lot of portions of this small language
model tutorial and I really want to
thank
um thank him for putting out such
incredible content out there from which
all of us are benefiting. So I've tried
to take that repository and put it into
a format which is much more easily
digestible and when everything is
exposed instead of directly importing
some things from his
library. So this is what we are going to
do with respect to the uh tokenization.
So let me show you what exactly we are
going to do. Okay. So now our data set
looks like this right. Every row in our
data set essentially corresponds to a
story. Uh the first row corresponds to
the first story. The second row
corresponds to the second story. The
third row corresponds to the third story
etc. There are 2 million such rows for
training and 20,000 such rows for
validation. So 2 million stories for
training and 20,000 stories for
validation. We have already seen this in
our data set over here. 2 million 2.12
million training rows and around 22,000
validation
rows. All right. So now what we are
going to do is that I'm going to take a
small sample from our data set and I'm
going to show you how we are going to do
the tokenization. So I have pasted a
screenshot of this sample over here.
This is let's say one such story and our
goal is to do two things right. We have
to tokenize this data set which is we
need to convert it into tokens and we
need to store all the token ids in one
place. So remember I mentioned to you
that uh the every token will be assigned
a token ID. Essentially what we need to
do is that we need to take every single
story and within every single story we
need to convert every token into a token
ID and merge all of these token ids
together. That will be our training data
set. And the way this is done is as
follows. So first we are going to use
this GPT2 subword tokenizer. We already
saw about this that is the bite pair
encoding tokenizer and we are going to
apply this on every single story. So
let's say when this bite pair encoding
tokenizer is applied on this story we
get certain tokens like these. Okay. So
that can be 442 518 11 257 etc. We are
going to store these tokens into uh
let's say dictionary with ids. So these
are my ids and my length is going to be
30. That's the length of the token ids
in one story. So every story I'm going
to store like this. This is the first
story. This is the first story where I
store the token ids and the length of
how many token ids I have. So 1 2 3 4 5
6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13. So that's why this
is 13. I'm similarly going to apply
tokenization to my entire data set. So
my first story will again have ids which
are these and it will have this length.
My second story will have a set of token
ids which have this length. My third
story will have again token ids and a
length. Similarly my last story which is
now 2.12 million will have a bunch of
token ids and the length. So now what I
want to do is that I don't want to store
separate token IDs at separate places
for each story. I want to merge all of
these token ids together so that I can
store them in one place. Right? And now
we are going to see an efficient way of
doing this
merging. So the goal is to store all the
token ids in a single dot bin file. The
reason we have bin file is because we'll
store the file directly on the disk
instead of storing it on the RAM. That
avoids LA RAM overload on big data sets.
So believe me, I've tried running this
code without using the bin and it takes
a huge amount of time to run this and
the entire code becomes very slow. But
if you just do this bin, if you create a
dot bin file and if you store all the
token in dotbin, you essentially store
everything on the disk, right? Since
everything is stored on the disk, um the
data can be loaded very fast during the
training. You just retrieve it from the
disk. And secondly our RAM uh which is
very precious for uh faster computations
that does not get overloaded overloaded
with huge amount of data especi
especially since we have around 2
million rows right that is why we using
dot bin and another advantage of storage
on the disk is that we don't need to
retokenize every time it is stored on
the disk during multiple sessions. So
once we tokenize that's it the token ids
are all stored on the disk. every time
you restart let's say you don't need to
uh retokenize again so that's why we
store everything in a dot bin file right
uh currently we have something like this
for every story we have a bunch of token
ids and we have length of the number of
tokens so that is for story one story
two etc right so what we'll do is that
we'll create a dot bin file as I
mentioned so the dot bill file can be
named something like
trainbin we'll see this in the code also
we'll create a dot bin file which is
named at train.bin pin and we'll create
a memory mapped array. Why do we create
a memory mapped array? Uh because it
means that the file is backed onto the
disk. So as I mentioned over here, we
need to do disk storage and for that we
need to create an array which is memory
mapped which means it will get stored on
the disk. And uh so this train.bin file
which is there we are going to store it
on the disk. It looks like a numpy
array. uh and when we use this np.mme
map it means that the file is stored on
the disk and we don't have to hold
everything in the RAM essentially so we
create a memory mapped array and then
then what we do is that we split our
entire data set into batches so let's
say I have my 2.12 million stories right
I have my 2.12 million stories I split
these stories into 1024 batches so batch
number one batch number two etc. Let's
say badge number one has about 1,000
stories or 2,000 stories. Then what we
do is that we take the token ids from
all of those stories and put it into
this train.bin file. Then I go to batch
number two. I take all the token IDs
from batch number two and put all of
them into the train.bin file. Similarly,
I go to the last batch batch 1024. I
take all the token ids there and put it
into the train.bin file. Ultimately, my
train.bin bin file will have all uh
we'll have all the token ids from all
the different stories which and
everything here will be saved to the
disk. So let me repeat what we are doing
here. I hope until this part you have
understood where every story is broken
into a bunch of token ids and every
token ID has some length which is
associated with it. Ultimately what we
have to do is that we have to store all
of these token ids together in some
place. That place is going to be this
train.bin bin file and this file is
going to be on the disk instead of
storing it on the
RAM. So in the code what you'll see is
that you'll see the file name and then
you'll see an array array which is
initialized like np.mme map. So this is
a memory mapped array. So this array
eventually will contain all of my token
ids which are stored on the disk right.
um and then all and the file name where
eventually this array is stored that's
train.bin. So my array will contain all
the token ids and this array will be
stored in the file name
train.bin. That's all which is done
here. We uh we create a bin file. We
create a memory mapped array. We split
the data set into batches and we add
everything to to the train.bin file.
That's it. So my train.bin file now
contains all of my token ids together.
You might be wondering why do we do
these batches. The reason we do these
batches is for faster processing.
Because if we don't do these batches uh
then it takes a huge amount of time to
serially go through my entire data set
collect token ids and put it to my
train.bin
file. The reason I'm explaining all of
this to you in detail is because that's
exactly what we are going to see in the
code right now. So if you go to the code
and if you see step number two here is
where we are going to tokenize the data
set and ideally this should take a huge
amount of time because we have 2.12
million stories. We have to essentially
convert all of those stories into token
ids and append all the token ids
together. But this version of the code
is actually very
fast. The first thing which we are doing
is we have we are getting encoding for
GPT2. So this tick token is the library.
If you see tick
token GitHub, you'll see that this is a
library which is open as library and we
can get tokenizers from here and we can
get them for different GPT2 model GPT
models. So here we are getting the
tokenizer for GPT2 and first thing what
we are doing is that we are going
through all of my stories and every
story we are converting it into a
dictionary of ids and length. So as you
can see over here every story is getting
converted into ids and length. We saw
this over here
also. That's the first step which is
happening in this process. Right? Then
what we are doing is that
uh here you see we are creating a file
name which will be created for training
as well as for validation. For the
training data we'll create a file called
train.bin bin and we'll create an array
which is a memory mapped array and we'll
divide the entire data set into 1024
batches. Now what we'll do is that for
each batch we'll collect the token ids
and we will store them into this array.
That is where so every batch will
collect the token ids as has been shown
in this part. Every batch will collect
the token ids and store it into the
array. This is what is happening in each
iteration of the for loop here. And then
we just go through different batches.
And as we go through different batches,
every batch will give us a bunch of
token ids. All of those we'll put into
this uh
array. And finally, array.flush means
that we store everything on the disk.
That's the last command. Array. Which
means we save everything to the disk
ultimately. So now this array will be
then uh stored in my file which is
train.bin. File name is train.bin for
the training data. And I have my
validation data in
validation.bin. So now after this after
this point in the code, the train.bin
file essentially it contains a huge list
of token ids. It's a huge file because I
have 22 million stories, right? And if
you just imagine for now one word has
one
token. Let's imagine one word has one
token, right? And if you see every word
here, every every story here has at
least 1,
two, let's say 60 words. Every story at
least has 50 words and have 2 million
stories, right? So that means there are
around 100 million words in the training
data. So the trainbin might have around
100 million tokens, token ids rather.
and my
validation my validation is I think uh
22,000 right so that is around 100th of
this so my validation will have around 1
million token ids which is still
significant so the trainbin will have a
list of all the token ids of my data and
my validation dobbin will have all the
list of token ids in my data set and
again why are we doing this step because
we need to convert my data which is in a
text format into a numerical format and
the first step of doing that is
tokenization. So first we have to decide
the tokenizer which we are going to use
and that's going to be the bite pair
encoding and we are going to use a
subword tokenizer. So every subword will
be one token ID. All the token ids will
be appended together. That's what we are
doing in a simple manner. But in this
code we are just trying to improve the
computational efficiency by storing
everything on the disk. That's why we
need a memory mapped array over here. If
this part is a bit confusing to you,
don't worry. Just remember that after
this part, after this code is executed,
we have tokenized the data set into
token ids. We have created a file called
train.bin. And this should be
validation.bin. We have created a file
called train.bin and uh validation.bin
where all the token ids are stored. And
we make sure that token ids are stored
on a disk rather than on the RAM. for
efficient computations. These three are
the most important things to remember
from step number
two. So until this point we have our
data set, we have converted it into
token ids. We have a train.bin file and
we have a validation.bin file. I hope
all of us have understood until this
point that is the step two which is data
prep-processing. Now we are coming to
step number three which is creating
input output pairs from the data set.
The reason we need to create input and
output pairs is because ultimately the
loss function which we will define for
training the language model will be
based on these input and the output
pairs. When we have regression tasks or
classification tasks in machine
learning, we are usually provided with
the labels of the correct answer. Right?
But in the case of language modeling, we
are just provided with the data set
which looks like this. But we are not
essentially told that what is the
correct answer, what is supposed to be
the right answer generated by the
language model etc. We have to create
these input and output pairs from the
data set. To understand how to create
input and output pairs, first it's very
important for all of us to understand
what's the purpose of language modeling
itself.
So when large language models were uh
constructed and when they became really
popular, what they actually did was they
took in the input as a sequence of
tokens or a sequence of words and then
the output which they generated was
essentially the next token prediction
task. So what is the next token
prediction task? It's essentially just
looking at the sequence of words which
has come until now and then predicting
the next token. So if you think of the
language model as the engine, the engine
receives the fuel and then the car moves
forward. Right? Similar to that, the
equivalent analogy to the language model
is that the sequence of tokens which
goes to the input that is the fuel and
the next token prediction that is the
movement which is the output which we
want.
What is so incredible and also beautiful
about language modeling is that although
we teach the model or train the model to
just predict the next token at a time,
it somehow understands the structure and
the meaning of human language within
that process almost as a byproduct of
that process.
And one more way to understand next
token prediction is that if you go to
chat GPT right and if you say something
like uh make a
travel plan for Italy you'll see that
chat GPT response and the response is
presented as a detailed paragraph but
actually just one token which is
predicted at a time and then it's
appended to each other. So at every
single instance only the next token or
the next word is predicted. You'll
notice that as the lecture goes along,
I'm using the word token and the word in
interchangeably. Although that's not the
case. We are using the subword
tokenization. So, usually one word is
not one token, but we'll use that for
the sake of simplicity. It's just better
for
explanation. Now, let me tell you how
these input and output pairs are
actually created from the data set. Here
I have taken one single story from the
tiny stories and let me tell you how the
input pairs are created. First to create
the input pairs we have to essentially
decide two things. First thing which we
have to decide is the context size. The
context size is the length of words or
tokens which my language model is
looking at at one time before it
predicts the next token. Or put in
another way, it is the maximum number of
tokens my language model can look at
before predicting the next
token. And here I'm deciding the context
size to be equal to four. What that does
is that based on the context size, I
will divide my entire data set into
chunks and the length of those chunks
will be equivalent to the context size.
In this case, it is equal to four. So
this is my first chunk. This is my
second chunk x2. This is my third chunk
which is x3. And this is my four chunk
X4. Similarly, the whole data set will
be broken down into these chunks. And
you'll see that each chunk essentially
consists of four words or four tokens
because the context size is equal to
four. Now although I'm showing words
over here to do keep in mind that we
have created train.bin and val.bin,
right? validation.bin. So what the model
actually sees is just a bunch of token
ids like this.
So it creates the inputs based on these
token ids and not the words. I just
wanted to clarify this because the model
after this stage has no idea of the
words. It just looks at token ids.
Sometimes we we forget about that
because as humans it's so natural for us
to look at words. But just remember that
when the model is creating the input
output pairs it just looks at token ids.
So the entire data set is broken down
into these input pairs whose size or the
chunk size is equal to four. The second
quantity which I need to decide before I
create these input output pairs is the
batch size. Batch size is essentially
when you're training language models, we
don't process all the input and output
data at one time. The data is usually
processed in batches. So first you uh
take the output of the first batch,
calculate the loss, propagate it
backwards, update up update the
parameters. Then you calculate the
output of the second batch, calculate
the loss, propagate it backwards and
update the parameters. The reason this
is done is that if you have no batches,
it would take a huge amount of time to
update the parameters because you have
to go through all of these all of the
entire data before updating the
parameters. So having batches makes it
much more convenient to perform the
training procedure. So here I'm deciding
a batch size equal to five. Once you
decide the context size and the batch
size, you can create input matrix
matrices such as this. So this is called
as my first input batch. So this is now
first this is my first input batch. The
reason this batch has number of rows
equal to four x1 x2 x3 x4 is because the
batch size is equal to four. there will
be four um there will be four sequences
in each batch and in each sequence so
for example if you look at X1 the number
of columns is equal to four why because
the context size is equal to four so
what I'm just doing is I'm taking these
four and stacking them on top of each
other that's how we create the first
input batch so similarly I can go
through my entire data set and create
multiple input batches that's how my
input batches are created now let me
talk a bit about how the output batches
are created or how the output pairs of
data are created. So let me rub this so
that I'll show you how the output is
created for the first input. Right? So
if you take a look at this first input
one day a little girl and I'm ignoring
this comma here for the sake of
simplicity. The output is just going to
be the input shifted to the right hand
side by one.
So the output of this first input
sequence is
this day a little girl um yeah a day a
little girl named that's going to be the
output sequence
um and if you look at for example if I
do it over here actually here the first
input should be of a sequence size equal
to four right so I should probably so
this is my first input and
uh my first output is going going to be
the first input shifted to the right
hand side by one. So this is going to be
my first output. Similarly, if my second
input, if my second input is let's say
this, which is x3, then the output
corresponding to this is just x3 shifted
to the right by one. So that is going to
be my y3. Now this is how the output
pairs are created. So if you look at
every input pair if x1 is 1 11 15 and 24
the output corresponding to that is just
the input shifted to the right hand side
by one. So if you see 1 11 15
24 11 etc. Let's say this is how the
token ids are arranged right in my
train.bin. If my first input is this
which is x1 my first output is just this
input shifted to the right hand side by
one. So that will be
uh 11 15 24 and 11. That's exactly what
is shown over here. So you see they have
an overlap of three over here. That is
how every output is constructed from
every input. So essentially once you
have x1, x2, x3, x4, the output tensor
or the output batch number one. This is
my output batch one. It's quite easy to
construct because it is just the input
inputs x1 x2 x3 x4 shifted to the right
hand side by one. So imagine all the
data set imagine sliding over the data
set in chunks of four. That will be my
input and just moving those chunks to
the right hand side by one and
aggregating them together in batches.
That's going to be my output. Now if you
look at let's look at the first input
and the first output right. So my x1 is
1 11 15 and 24 and my y1 is essentially
11 15 24 and 11. Okay. And let's assume
some 1 day a little. So let's say this
corresponds
to one day a
little and this corresponds to day
a little girl. Now you might be thinking
that if this is my input and this is the
output
uh what exactly are the input output
pairs over here. So it turns out or what
are we really predicting here? Remember
I told you that language models are just
next token prediction. So it turns out
that in one input output pair like this
there are multiple next token prediction
tasks. So if one is the input then day
should be the output. If one day is the
input, then should be the output. If one
day is the input, a little should be the
output. And if one day a little is the
input, then girl should be the output.
We train the model on all these four
tasks. So when you look at one input
output pair, it just it's not just one
input and prediction. It's not just one
prediction tasks. There are four
prediction tasks which are happening
here. So let me write down this um these
four tasks. So one is the input and day
should be the output. One day is the
input. O should be the output. One day O
is the input, little is the output and
one day or little is the input and girl
is the output. So remember this column
is my input and this column is my
target. So when my model is initially in
my model is initialized its output which
it gives will be something completely
different than the target. What we have
to do is that the model
output has to be as close to the target
as possible. That is what we have to
ensure in the back propagation. So when
you look at these input and target pairs
for every row there are four input
output prediction tasks right and
similarly there are four such rows in
every
batch. So we are essentially training
the model to predict the next token at
every stage of the process. So if you
start looking at this paragraph from now
from the start itself what we are
essentially doing by creating these
input output pairs is that when one is
the input day is the output we teaching
the model that when one day is the input
o is the output when one day is the
input little is the output when one day
a little is the input girl is the output
that's x1 y1 training then we go to x2
y2 training so x2 is now girl named lily
found right so when girl is the input
named is the output. When girl named is
the input, li is the output. When girl
named li is the output, find found is
the output. So essentially we're
training the model at every stage to
predict the next token and we are doing
that through creation of this input and
output
batches. I hope this part is very clear
to you. It's very important to visualize
this part before we go to the model
architecture itself because here is
where all the confusion in language
modeling starts. You have to know how
the input and target are created. And
let me give you a short summary now of
this whole process. Let's say we have
this data set,
right? Let's say we have this data set.
The first thing which is done is that I
decide my context size. If it's equal to
four, I create input chunks which are
like this. So I divide the whole data
set into chunks of four. That will be
x1, x2, x3, x4 etc. And then along with
this I essentially shift to shift this
to the right hand side by one. So that
is how I create my output. That is how I
create my output chunks. Right? So I
have my input chunks. I have my output
chunks. Then I divide my input chunks
into batches. I divide my output chunks
into batches. If you look at one batch
closely, there will be four in X1, Y1,
X2, Y2, X3, Y3 and X4, Y4. If you
analyze each row here, X1 and Y1, there
are essentially four input output tasks
here which we are training the model.
And in each task we train the model to
predict the next token. So when the
whole training proceeds the model knows
that whatever is the input let's say if
this is the input the model is trained
to predict the next token as the output.
So here you might be thinking that this
is is that is that the only training
objective in language models and it
turns out that the training objective is
as simple as this. We are just
predicting the next token at a time. And
what's quite amazing is that how does
the model really know language from this
simple training? How does it understand?
So if there's a sentence such as let's
say blue
electrons, blue electrons eat
fish. Let's say there is a sentence like
this, right? Which is blue electrons eat
fish. How does the model actually know
that it should not predict a sentence
such as this? Because ultimately we are
just training on the next token
prediction, right? We are not telling
the model anything about the world
around us. But through this simple task
of the next token prediction, the model
somehow understands that electrons
cannot be blue, not just that electrons
cannot eat fish. And so the model
understands the form of the language and
the meaning of the language as we are
showing over
here. Okay. So this is the main process
of creating input output pairs and this
is what we are going to exactly see in
the code. Now in the code you will
encounter a statement such as this ix is
equal to torch.trant int like this. So
what is exactly done in this statement
is that we create an id vector of length
batch size. Um so essentially what this
means is that if for every batch we
sample from random places. So let's say
so here I've collected x1 x2 x3 x4 in
together right? It can be like this is
x1 let's say this is x2 this is x3 and
this is x4 that's also fine and that's
how we are going to do the code. So if
this is x1 this is x2 x3 and x4 the
corresponding y will be of course this
shifted to the right hand side by
one. So whenever a batch is created
there we are going to define a function
which is called as get batch.
Whenever the function get batch is
defined, what it will do is that it will
create so and if the batch size is four,
it will take from random places four
vectors and create this input batch. It
will shift the input batch to the right
by one and create the output batch. So
that is what you'll see happening in the
code. That's the first thing. The second
thing which you'll see happening in the
code is we are doing something like
X.pin memory. So these input and output
tensors or matrices which we have we are
going to pin pin them to the
memory. So what this does is that it
locks the memory of the tensor in the
RAM and that allows faster transfer of
the tensor to the GPU. Uh now we are
going to transfer this input and this
output tensors to the GPU at some point
for calculations in the transformer
block. So having the pin memory locks
the memory of the tensor in RAM and we
can allow faster transfer of the tensor
to the GPU. So it's like telling our
operating system that hey don't move
this memory around my GPU would want it
very soon and so the memory is kind of
locked. The input and the output are
locked in memory so they can be
transferred to the GPU easily. And then
we are also doing this non-blocking
equal to true. The reason non-blocking
equal to true is done is because if you
normally do dot to device, it blocks the
CPU until the copy to the GPU finishes.
So non-blocking equal to true ensures
that CPU can continue to do other work
like next batch preparation etc. So the
CPU does not have to be blocked while uh
uh while we copy our data to the GPU. So
you'll see this also in the code. So let
us jump to code right now. If you scroll
down below to step number three, here is
where we create the input and the output
batches. Right? So this is the get a
batch function. Remember every get a
batch function is going to return one
input matrix and one output matrix like
this. Okay. So this is that first
statement I mentioned. So this
essentially samples four random
integers which essentially corresponds
to or four. I'm saying four because I'm
assuming batch size equal to four. So it
will correspond to randomly sampling
from four different places in my data
set. That's IX. What X essentially does
is
that it stacks it stacks together X1,
X2, X3 and X4. Y stacks together Y1, Y2,
Y3 and Y4. And if you look at X1 and Y1,
let's say if you see Y is just shifted
to the right hand side by one. So what
is being mentioned as block size in
here? That is the context size which we
have in the code and the batch size is
the same as so the block size is what we
discussed as context size on the white
board and uh the batch size the batch
size is the same as the batch size which
we had discussed. So here we are
creating the input and the output
batches x1 x2 x3 x4 y1 y2 y3 y4 right
and now here we are just pinning the x
and y2 memory and non-blocking equal to
true so that we can move to the GPU very
easily. These statements are just
written for computational
efficiency. So within these small lines
of code there are actually number of
things which are happening. So if you
just see this code block you might be
very confused by it and you won't
understand what's going on here. But
first what we are doing is that we are
doing this batches for both training
data and validation data. That's why
these first lines of code are there.
Then here what we do is that we sample
random integers. So if the batch size is
equal to four, we are going to sample
four random integers. They correspond to
four positions which we are going to
look at in the data set. So for example,
position one can be here, position two
can be here, position three can be here,
position four can be here. Wherever the
position is, we get x1, x2, x3, x4. From
there, we shift to the right by one and
get y1, y2, y3, and y4. And then we just
pin it to the memory. That's it. We are
going to see this get batch function
when we run the pre-training loop. Every
time we say get a batch, we are going to
get one input and output batch. Then we
are going to
compute, we are going to run the input
through the llm, get the output, then
compute the loss, back propagate. Okay.
So that's why get batch serves a very
important
role. Now that you have understood until
here we now move to the next part which
is probably the most important in this
video and that part is essentially
defining the architecture of the small
language model. So let's get started
with this. The small language model
architecture can appear a bit
intimidating. It can appear a bit
frightening because as you can see over
here there are multiple different things
which are happening in the model
architecture. Right? As we saw earlier
this whole architecture can be broadly
divided into three parts. Part number
one, part number two and part number
three. Part number one is the input
block. Part number two is the
processor and part number three is the
output block.
To truly understand the language model
architecture, we have to understand all
of these parts in detail. And I could
easily spend 10 to 12 hours explaining
every single aspect of this
architecture. But my main aim in this
tutorial is to give you enough
understanding of this architecture so
that you can understand what's going on
in the code. I won't have the time to go
into the details of each and every
component here because that would make
this tutorial very long. Uh but I will
give you enough intuition, enough u
writing on the whiteboard so that you
understand step by step what is going on
in each part. Right? So let's get
started. The code associated for this
part is in this uh code cell which is
called defining the language model
architecture. And this is the longest
code cell. So if someone looks at the
code, they might not understand
anything. And at that time they might
feel that language model is language
modeling is very difficult and it's not
meant for me. But it's only when you
start understanding the nuts and bolts
of how this code is assembled, you'll
see that everything really makes a lot
of sense. Essentially we are just
assembling all of these components
together so that when we get the input
text which is a sequence of words at the
end the goal is to predict the next
token right that's all we are going to
see in the small language model
architecture. What we are going to see
is that when we have a sequence of words
which is the fuel to the language model,
how does it predict the output which is
the next token. And once we get the next
token prediction, we have already seen
that we are going to find the loss
between the output token produced by the
language model and the target token for
these input output pairs input output
patch pairs which we have seen before.
So the SLM model architecture is going
to take some time to explain but at the
end of it remember that we are just
feeding in a sequence of words such as
one day a little and we have to predict
the next token which ideally should be
girl. So if you see this sentence one
day a little if that is the
input ideally the next token should be
girl. So we are going to see how the LLM
takes these sequence of tokens and
produces the next token. My approach
here is that first I'm going to explain
to you everything on a whiteboard in a
very sequential manner and then what we
are going to do is that then we are
going to try to go to the code and we
are going to map out every single thing
which we have seen on the whiteboard to
every single detailed aspect of the
code. Right? So let's get started. First
what we do is that we have already
created this input and output batches.
Correct? So let's say we are looking at
the first batch initially and I'm
looking at the first row of the first
batch which I have mentioned over here.
That's my input right now. I'm looking
at the first row of the first
batch and the goal is to take this input
and to predict the next token ID
whatever it might be. So now let us see
the journey through which this input
sequence of tokens actually go through
before we have to predict the next
token. The first thing which we have to
do is that although this these tokens
are in numerical format so technically
they can be processed by the computer or
the language model. We convert every
token ID into a higher dimensional
vector and that step is called as token
embedding.
The reason we do token embedding is
because when we look at language, right?
Let's
say I take a screenshot of this this
story and I paste it over
here. Now, if you look at language and
the way language manifests itself, every
word carries some meaning and that's
what that's what gives meaning to the
whole paragraph. Right? When you read a
little girl named Lily, something comes
to your mind because little has some
meaning, girl has some meaning, cat has
some meaning, dog has some meaning. Both
of them come under animals. So
essentially words have some sort of a
semantic
notion which is very important for the
language model to
capture. So what can we do before we
pass the input to the transformer block?
Can we somehow take these token ids and
possibly represent them in higher
dimensional vector spaces that capture
some information about the meaning. So
what we are going to do is that let's
say cat right that has the token ID of
13 and let's say we have dog that has
the token ID of 17. So I'm going to take
these tokens and I'm going to project
them into higher dimensional vector
space. For now, let's say I'm choosing a
two-dimensional vector space and cat
comes over here and dog comes over here.
Cat and dog are animals. So they have
some similarity in meaning. So they lie
closer to each other. But both of these
words let's say will be very different
than a chair let's say. So chair will
lie over here but chair and table will
lie very close to each other. So you see
what we are doing here. We are
projecting these
words as vectors and then we are hoping
that vectors which are closer to each
other would be similar in meaning.
Vectors which are farther apart from
each other would be different in
meaning. Why do we do this? Because we
capture some notion about the meaning of
words and that is how we can exploit the
properties of language when we look at
convolutional neural network. So I'm
sure all of you must have seen this
convolutional neural network explainer,
right? Why do we take convolutional
filters and why do we slide them over
the images? Because we want to exploit
properties in an image. The properties
of translational invariance, the
properties that two pixels will always
slightly lie closer to each other and
even if a cup is present here or here,
it will still be a cup. So there are
some properties inherent in the images
which are exploited when we use these
feature maps or these convolutional
layers. That's why CNN's work so well.
So if you want to exploit language which
is our data right now the best way to do
it would be to capture meaning in
vectors. So that's why what's done as
the next step is that every token ID is
converted into a highdimensional vector
and that's a token embedding vector. The
way this is done is that we maintain
something called as the token embedding
matrix. We maintain something called as
the token embedding matrix. And the
token embedding matrix has number of
rows equal to our vocabulary size. So
row number one, let me do this with a
different
color. Row number one, row number two
dot dot dot. If the vocabulary size is
50,000, then it will be 50,000. and each
uh each token ID in my vocabulary is now
encoded as a high dimensional vector. So
this can be let's say a 768. So I have
to choose my embedding dimension and
that property stays with me throughout
my architecture. I have to choose my
embedding dimensions. So if I choose my
embedding dimensions to be equal to
768, every token here is represented as
a 768 dimensional vector.
So this is also called as the embedding
dimension. So we store this token
embedding matrix where every token ID in
my vocabulary is represented let's say
as a 768 dimensional vector. Notice that
the 768 is an experimental choice which
we have to make at the start. And now
once we have the token embedding matrix,
how do you retrieve the embedding
vectors for every token ids? You
essentially just use this as a lookup
table. So if token ids are 1, 11, 15 and
24, the way we retrieve their embedding
vectors is that we just look at row
number one, we look we look at row
number 11, we look at row number 11, we
look at row number 15 and we look at row
number
24 and we just get the vectors
corresponding to these
rows. So the token embedding matrix
essentially serves as the lookup table.
So that when we have token ids, we can
just look up this token embedding matrix
and retrieve the corresponding token
embedding vector. So now this input
which we have right now is transformed
into this matrix over here. So I had 1
11 15 and 24. Right? Now every token ID
is represented let's say as a 768
dimensional matrix.
So now if my input let's say I'm going
with the input as let's say every effort
moves you or one day a little whatever
this will be a 768 dimensional vector.
So let me change this
actually this was
one day a little correct so now one is a
768 dimensional vector day is a 768
dimensional vector O is a 768
dimensional vector and little is a 768
dimensional vector. So now you may ask
that how do we choose these vectors? Do
we know the embeddings before? So are
the embeddings such that they already
capture meaning? No. All of these values
are initialized randomly. And wherever
I'm marking P, it means that these are
trainable parameters of our model. So
initially this whole token embedding
matrix is initialized as a random
matrix. So all of these rows will be
effectively normalized. And what I was
saying earlier was that let's say if you
have layer 1, layer 2, layer 3, layer
four and you're back propagating, right?
Usually what happens is that the
gradients in every layer depend on the
output of that layer. And if the output
of the layer widely fluctuates between
large and small values, then the
gradient can either stagnate or the
gradient can explode. It just becomes
very unstable training dynamics.
Also if you don't do layer normalization
the distribution of inputs which is
received at every layer that
distribution of inputs might change. For
example layer 1 in one iteration might
have this input distribution in another
iteration it might have a skewed
distribution. So this training becomes
hard as the distribution changes from
one iteration to the next. Layer
normalization prevents this problem
which is called internal coariate shift.
it it it constrains the values of all
inputs within a certain range and it
also makes sure that distribution is
kind of similar. So that just improves
training. So wherever you see this layer
normalization block, it is usually used
to improve the training performance. So
the first step in the attention is the
layer normalization. And if you go to
the code, you will see that there is a
separate block which we have written
earlier. So there is a class called
layer normalization. Since layer
normalization is utilized at many places
in the transformer block, you see that
it's introduced it's introduced here.
It's introduced here also. So it's there
at two places, right? So it's better to
define a class for it. And we just use
the layer norm method which is available
through PyTorch. It just normalizes
every single row,
right? Okay. So layer normalization is
done. The next part is the place where
magic happens. So magic happens here
because the next step is multi head
attention. Now what exactly happens in
multi head attention and why is the
multi head attention block needed? If
you observe closely what I have done
until now uh let's say we have the
tokens right one day a
little we have taken for each token we
have taken the token embeddings we have
added the position embeddings but until
now we have no information about how one
token essentially relates to the other
token right and that information is very
important for us why because consider
this sentence the
dog the dog chased the
ball,
it could not catch it. Let's say if we
have this sentence and this first it now
relates to the dog, right? But if you
look at the second it, the second it now
relates to the ball. So if I want to do
next token prediction and if some it
comes somewhere in the next sentence, I
want to know whether it belongs to the
dog or whether it's the cat, right? If
it's the dog, I might predict something
like bark. If it's the ball, I might
predict something like flu because the
ball can fly. But if I don't know how
one token relates to another token, I
don't have the information about how to
predict the next token. And that's what
the attention mechanism actually does.
The attention mechanism augments the
input embedding vector so that for every
vector now I can have information about
the neighbors. So if I look at this
input vector, I need to have information
that I need to pay the maximum attention
to dog. If I look at this, it I need to
pay maximum attention to
ball. So the main purpose of the
attention mechanism is that let's say
uh let's say we look at this it and
currently we have the input embedding
vector for this it. It has no clue about
all the other tokens, right? What the
attention mechanism does is that it
maintains the size of this it so that
it's if it's 768 the size will remain
768 but it will convert it into a vector
which is called as the context vector.
Why is it called as the context vector?
Because to get this context vector from
the input embedding vector we take into
account how it how this it relates to
all the other tokens. So we somehow get
the attention scores between it and all
the other tokens and we use those
attention scores to go from the input
embedding vector to the context vector
for
it and this has been captured here in
this image very nicely. Uh when we have
one one token what we do is that through
the attention mechanism through the
multiad attention mechanism we actually
capture the attention score between one
token and all the other tokens around
it. So we capture the attention score
between next and the. We capture the
attention score between next and day. We
capture the attention score between next
and is. And we capture the attention
score between next and bright. Why do we
capture these attention scores? The
reason we capture these attention scores
is because let's say I have next, right?
And currently we have an input vector
for next. Now I will use all these
values. is I will use alpha 2 1, alpha
22, alpha 2 3, alpha 2 4 and alpha 25 to
convert this input vector into a context
vector and the context vector now
remember will be much richer. Why will
it be much richer? Because it will have
information about how my word next
relates to all the other tokens
surrounding it. This attention mechanism
if it was not there language models
would not work the way they are working
right now. And uh what the attention
mechanism actually does is that it takes
every tokens and converts them into
these context vectors. So in this part
is where we start understanding more
context about the sentence. So word
start understanding the meaning of their
neighbors and so next word prediction
effectively becomes much more
better. Now what exactly happens in this
multi-ad attention block? There are
several steps which happen in the multi
head attention block but more
importantly the input is these input
embeddings right. So if you look at the
multi head attention block the input are
these same input embeddings which are
these after layer normalization we apply
the mask multi head attention and the
output is the dimension is the same. So
if you see before multi head attention
each each token has a dimension 768.
After multi head attention also they
have a dimension 768. But now each of
these vectors are context vectors which
means they have enriched information of
all their
neighbors. The way we go from input
vectors to context vectors is through
these matrices which are called as
queries, keys and values. Now I'm not
going to go into detail of this because
that will again uh tremendously increase
the length of this video. But let me
give you a quick recap of how this is
actually done. First what we do is that
let's say I have my input embedding
matrix now. So I'll bring this over
here. Uh let's say this because it's
easy to copy paste. So I'll bring this
over here. That's my input embedding
matrix. Let's say what is done is that
first we introduce some matrices which
are called as the query matrix, the key
matrix and the value
matrix. And the input right now is 4x
768.
Each of these will be of a size of 768x
768. So when you multiply input with the
trainable query matrix, it gives me the
keys matrix. And that's again 4x 768.
When you multiply the input with the
trainable keys matrix, sorry, this is
the queries matrix. Then this is the
keys
matrix and this is the values matrix.
All of this must be sounding very weird
because why do we introduce additional
training matrices? The simple reason is
that humans could not figure out a
physical representation of how to
capture context. So we pass all of that
burden of figuring out how to capture
context between tokens to this trainable
weight matrices. So again I'm marking
these with P because these are the
parameters which will be learned. So
let's see where all we have marked P so
far. We have marked P over here in the
token embedding in the positional
embedding. We'll mark P over here in the
mass multi and attention also because
these are the parameters which are
actually learned. Once we have the
queries and the key vectors, we'll take
a dotproduct between the queries and the
keys and that will give me the attention
score matrix. The attention score matrix
will be a 4x4 matrix now because we have
four tokens, right?
Uh and my four tokens are every effort
moves you or um the little girl example
which we had one day a little. So now
why do I have a 4x4 here? So if I say
one day a
little and one day a little. The reason
we have a 4x4 matrix here is because for
every
token, this matrix give me gives me how
much attention should I pay to the
nearby token. So if I look at day, this
value tells me how much attention is
between day and 1. This value tells me
between day and day. This value tells me
between day and this value tells me
between day and little. This is my
attention score matrix. The attention
score matrix is then converted into an
attention weights matrix.
And then the attention weights matrix is
multiplied with my
values. Um so we have key queries and
values right with my values. And that
gives me a context vector
matrix. And this context vector matrix
is of the size of 4x 768. And this is
the output of the multi head attention
which we have mentioned over here. I
know I went through this this module a
bit fast because usually I spend about
four to five hours explaining attention
mechanism itself but here the main
purpose is for you to see a broader
picture of how different blocks are
assembled together so that you don't
feel that this is something too complex
you should get a basic understanding of
this and later if you want you can dive
into the multiad attention mechanism a
bit further
also. So if you see what exactly happens
in the multi attention mechanism is all
these steps. We multiply with trainable
queries keys values. We get the query
matrix the key matrix the value matrix.
We multiply queries with the keys
transpose and we get the attention
scores. The attention scores are
normalized by square root of keys
dimensions and plus we apply softmax and
we get the attention weights. We
multiply with values and we get the
context vector matrix. One more thing to
note here is that there is something
called as causality here. Which means
when we look at these uh attention
scores, ideally every token should have
attention score between only that token
and the tokens which come before it. It
should not have attention scores between
the token and what comes after it. So
for example, if I look at day, we should
not have the attention score between day
and earth because comes after day,
right? And ideally we are predicting the
next token. So we should have no
information about what comes after the
next token. So essentially what is done
is that so if you look at one it should
not have information about these three.
If you look at day it should not have
information about these two. If you look
at O it should not have information
about this. So all the elements above
the diagonal are essentially put to
zero. And that is called as causal
attention.
So when you look at the code, you are
going to see all of these steps exactly
implemented the same way as I mentioned
over here and you will see the name
causal attention. But don't get scared
or intimidated by this name. It's
essentially because we cannot peak into
the future. For one given token, we can
only pay attention to that token or what
comes before it, not to the tokens which
come after it. So we put all the
elements above the diagonal to be equal
to zero. If you want more information
about the attention mechanism and if you
want to dive deeper, you can have a look
at the build LLM from scratch lecture
series which is a huge number of
lectures. I think I have 5 hours of
content on the attention
mechanism. Okay. So this is the second
block which is the multi head attention
and actually this is the most important
block of the transformer architecture.
So if you look at the code you'll see
that this is that block which is called
causal self attention and remember it is
called causal because we cannot peak
into the future and it's called self
attention because we are looking at a
given sentence. We are looking at a
given sentence and we are see computing
the attention between tokens of that
sentence with tokens of the same
sentence. That's why it's called self
attention. Okay. So now if you see what
is happening here. Um so here we have
the queries, keys and the values matrix.
Okay, the queries, keys and the values
and then we multiply the queries with
the keys transpose to get the attention
scores which has been shown over here.
The queries will be multiplied with the
keys transpose to get these attention
scores. So these are also called causal
attention
scores. Causal attention scores. So here
you can see uh here we get the causal
attention scores and then what we do
here you can see that the elements above
the diagonal are replaced with minus
infinity so that we can when we take
soft max they will be equal to zero. So
when we have the attention scores we
replace the elements above here with
negative infinity because when we take
soft max they'll be zero for the causal
attention purposes that gives us the
attention weights and remember here we
are also dividing by the square root of
keys dimension. So we get the attention
scores. We get the attent the mechanism
proceeds like this. We get the attention
scores. We get the attention scores. We
divide by the square root of keys
dimension. This is done because the
variance of the query is multiplied by
the keys. The dot product the variance
of that dot dot that dot product should
stay as low as possible. That's again to
stabilize the
training. So we scale by square root of
keys dimension. Then after that what we
do is that we fill the elements above
the
diagonal. We fill the elements above the
diagonal with negative
infinity and then we take the soft max.
What this will ensure is that it will do
two things. It will make sure that every
row of the attention score sums up to
one because we take soft max and since
we have negative infinity and when we
take that soft max all elements above
the diagonal will be zero.
So then the attention scores or the
attention weight matrix will be
something like this. All this will be
zero and whatever is remaining every row
of whatever is remaining will
essentially sum up to one. So then you
can make quantitative statements like
when this is my query how much attention
should I pay to each of the
tokens. So all of that is happening over
here. We first take the queries
multiplied by keys transpose divide by
square root of keys dimension. Fill the
elements above the diagonal with
negative infinity. Take soft max. Uh and
then there is also a layer of dropout
which we can apply over here. Again
dropout is applied to improve
generalization performance. And the
final step as I've mentioned over here
is that we take the attention weights
and we multiply it with the values
values matrix. The attention weights is
multiplied with the values matrix and we
get the context vector matrix. That's
it.
Um and then uh once we get the context
vector matrix then we can add one more
layer of dropout after that and we can
also add an output projection layer. So
a final neural network is added at the
output. We'll come to that in just a
moment. But for now just remember that
in the causal self attention block until
here we have the context vector matrix.
There is one more output projection
layer which is a small neural network is
added at the end of the so once we get
this context vector matrix a small
neural network is added which kind of
preserves the shape so it still remains
4x 768 and this is not usually required
but sometimes the neural network is
there so it's an optional neural network
which can be added as an output
projection layer that's what's mentioned
over here and then one more layer of
dropout is actually applied
So this is what happens in the causal
attention block. And I know that I have
gone a bit fast through the block
through this block. But if you have
understood this much, it means you have
understood the basics of the attention
mechanism. Remember what the attention
mechanism is trying to do is that we
take the input embedding matrix and
convert it into a context vector matrix.
That's it. And these trainable weight
matrices are uh devised or we have added
them because we could not come up with a
closed form expression for how to
capture context. So we offload that to
the trainable weight matrices and we
hope that they will do the job for
us. Okay. So this is the mask multi head
attention until this point we get the
context vector for every single token.
Then you see in the transformer block if
let me rub this one so that we have a
clearer view of what all steps are
happening. Until now what all have we
covered in the transformer block? We
have covered the layer normalization and
multi head attention. Now after this
point there is one more layer of
dropout. There is one more layer of
dropout. So we randomly mask out some
elements to zero again to improve
generalization performance. So that is
this dropout layer. And then you'll see
this symbol over here, right? That
symbol is a shortcut connection or a
skip connection. And the reason we have
shortcut connections is because we give
another alternative path for the
gradient to flow. Shortcut connections
are added to prevent the vanishing
gradient problem when multiple layers
are chained
together. So whenever we have shortcut
connection here, it means that there is
a path which has been created. So if you
see now yeah whenever you have this
shortcut connection it means that there
is a shortcut between uh this path and
this whenever you see there is the
shortcut connection there is a shortcut
between this path and this which means
the gradient can also flow flow from
here. What it means that there is a
shortcut it means that the input of this
layer is added to the output here. So
this input is added to this output and
that serves as the input to the next
layer. Similarly, what happens here is
that this input is added to this output
and that's the plus summation over here.
So, a simple operation like this
prevents the vanishing gradient problem
by giving the gradient an alternative
path to flow. You can think of this as
similar to the ResNet
architecture. Okay. So, there is a there
is a shortcut connection here and there
is also a shortcut connection at the end
of the transformer block. There are two
shortcut connections. There is one
shortcut connection here and there is
one shortcut connection here. Okay.
After this first shortcut connection, we
have another layer of After this first
shortcut connection, we have another
layer normalization. So then again we
ensure that for the context vectors
which we have the mean is equal to zero
and the variance is equal to one. That
is very important that we apply layer
normalization once more. And after layer
normalization is applied, there is one
more crucial layer and that's the feed
forward neural network. Now something
very interesting happens in this feed
forward neural network. This feed
forward neural network actually looks
something like this. So let's say we
focus on one input. Right? Now it has
768 dimensions.
Right? This input will go through my
feed forward neural network. So I have
an input with 768 dimensions. The hidden
layer has dimensions 4 * 768 and that I
think is
uh uh 302 3072. So the hidden layer has
3072 dimensions and my output layer
again has 768 dimensions. So I call this
an expansion compression neural network
where the neural network retains the
size of the input. So every input which
passes through the neural network when
it comes through the output it will have
the same size 768. But remember that due
to these expansion and contraction and
due to this additional trainable
parameters it allows the language model
to explore a much richer space. That's
what's done frequently in deep learning.
Right? If something does not work in a
low dimensional space, you project
everything to a higher dimensional space
so that you can capture additional
insights. you can capture more
nonlinearities. Your function can learn
new things. So it turns out that without
this neural network, the language model
does not learn about the context
patterns in the underlying data and it
cannot answer queries that well. But
addition of this neural network
completely changes the performance of
the language model and that's why this
neural network is introduced at this
stage of uh uh this stage of the
transformer block where uh the input. So
now we have four rows right? So 4x 768
when it passes through the neural
network and when it comes out it's again
4x 768 but through this process we make
the uh additional we have additional
parameters so that the language model
can explore a much richer space. Now one
more thing to notice is that usually the
activation functions which we have in
neural networks are ru tanh etc. But the
activation function here is
JLU and that's a different function than
RLU because the RLU is this right? It's
it looks something like this. But a JU
actually looks something
like it looks something like
this. So at higher X's when X becomes
high it becomes very similar to Y= X. So
it approximates ALOU but at negative XS
it does not directly become zero. But
it's smooth. It's differentiable at x
equal to0 and it slowly becomes zero. So
generally this has shown to have good
results. Again this is an experimental
choice. There is no real need to only
stick with this. But as a hyperparameter
researchers have got very good results
with language modeling if they use the
JLU activation function. Okay. So that's
the activation function used in the feed
forward neural network. And once we come
outside the feed forward neural network,
there is another dropout layer over
here. So then the output of the feed
forward neural network, some of these
outputs are again randomly turned off to
zero. As you can see over here, some of
these outputs are randomly turned off to
zero to improve generalization
performance. And then we have one more
shortcut connection here. So the input
of this is added to the output of this
block. Again the shortcut connection
provides another path for the gradient
to flow thus preventing the vanishing
gradient
problem. So now actually let us see the
building blocks which we have assembled
so far. We have the layer normalization
block. We saw how the
um causal attention block is there.
There is one more class which we
specially create for this feed forward
neural network. So here you can see we
have a feed forward neural network over
here. uh this is the first layer and
that input goes into four times the
embedding dimension. So we have an input
with the embedding dimension as we saw
over here that was 768. The input goes
into a hidden layer with four times
embedding dimension that's the expansion
layer. Then we have the JU activation
function which we saw and then there is
a
uh there is a compression layer over
here. So that is again projecting the 4
into 768 back into
768 followed with a dropout. So the
neural network is again followed with a
dropout as we have seen over here. The
neural network layer follows a dropout
layer. So we call this class as
multi-layer perceptron. Okay. So here if
you see the code we assemble three
classes. We assemble the layer
normalization class. We assemble the
causal attention class and we assemble
the multi-layer perceptron class. Once
we have these three classes, we can
technically assemble the entire
transformer block like this because we
have let me rub this. Why can we assem
Why can we assemble this entire block?
Because now we have everything we need,
right? We have the class for the layer
normalization. So I'm marking this over
here one. We have a layer normalization
class. We have a multi attention class
with dropout. And we have uh the feed
forward neural network we drop out
everything we have. So now we just
assemble these different classes
together. And that's why that's what's
done in this class called block. So the
class called block is my transformer
block is my transformer block. And if
you see closely what's happening here,
we first have a layer normalization as
we saw here with number one. That's the
layer normalization. Then we have the
multi head attention with drop out. So
if you see the causal attention by
default towards the end the dropout is
already
implemented. So this is number two the
multi head attention with dropout that's
number two that's done right now. Then
we have
uh uh then we have another layer
normalization. If you see over here we
have another layer normalization that's
again marked as one. And then finally we
have the feed forward neural network
with feed forward neural network with
the dropout. So that's marked as three
over here. So that's how we have
assembled the entire transformer block
in just three lines of code or four
lines of code because we have defined
classes earlier. The ln one is the first
layer normalization. ln2 is the second
layer normalization. This is the causal
attention block and here we have the
multi-layer perceptron block. Okay. And
if you see the shortcut connections are
these. So the input to the so if you see
attention right uh the self.attension
attention. That's where the first uh
shortcut connection exists. So the
output of this is added to the input.
That's what this line represents. And
the second shortcut connection is after
the feed forward neural network over
here. So the output of this is added to
the input of this. That's what this
that's what this line actually
represents. So this transformer block
code here contains the entire code for
the full transformer block. So these
eight lines of code is where all the
magic really
happens. And remember that in GPT there
is not one transformer block. There are
multiple transformer blocks which we
have to decide. So until now in the code
if you see we have reached until this
stage right where we saw the token
embedding plus the position embedding
these were passed as an input to the
transformer block. Okay. But now we have
multiple transformer blocks. So if you
see
uh here uh yeah h right so we have
multiple transformer blocks which is
given by the number of layers. So the
number of layers tells us how many
transformer blocks we have. What our
input does is that it has to pass
through all of these transformer blocks.
It has to pass through all of these
transformer blocks. So whatever I have
shown over here, whatever I have shown
over here, right? There are actually
multiple transformer blocks over
here. There is not just one transformer
block. So one transformer block has this
entire architecture, right? These might
be 12 or 24 such blocks. So my input has
to pass through the first transformer
block, then through the second, then the
third, right up till the very end. And
then and only then does it exit out of
the transformer and then it has to come
to the output block. So if you see over
here what we have written over here is
that the input which was the token plus
the positional embedding has to go
through all of these multiple
transformer blocks and then it comes out
of the processor and this is that step
in which we have the output defined. So
I'll come to that in a
moment.
Um all right so the output has been
defined actually the output has been
defined over here and also over here. So
I'll come to that in a moment. But until
this point just remember that we have
gone through the multiple transformer
blocks and then we have the output. What
is the output size after going through
multiple transformer blocks? After the
first transformer block, the output size
remains the same as the input. Right?
When we went inside the transformer
block, remember the size was four rows
and 768 columns. Even after applying
dropout, that's the same size. When we
come out of multiple transformer blocks,
the size remains the same. That's 4 *
768. Okay. Now we have come out of the
multiple transformer blocks and finally
we'll go to this last third block which
is the output layer. Now you see here
there are two things which happen. First
we have to pass through another layer of
normalization and then we have to pass
through the output layer. So let me
explain step by step what is happening
over here. When we come out of the
transformer block, we have this size
right which is 4 * 768. Then we will do
one more layer of normalization. And
here the same thing happens. Essentially
we subtract the mean divide by the
square root of variance. So now the mean
is equal to zero. Variance is equal to 1
for every row. Okay. And then we pass
this 4 * 768 matrix into an output head.
What this output head does is that this
output head converts every vector is now
of a size of 768. Right? It converts
every vector into the vocabulary size.
Now it converts every vector into the
vocabulary size. And the way it does is
that by passing every vector through a
neural network. So if this size is of 4x
768, I will have a neural network of
size 768 multiplied by my vocabulary
size.
So when this input passes through this
neural network, it will be of a size of
4 into vocabulary
size. So now take a look here. Every
token now will have 50257 or my
vocabulary size if my vocabulary size is
something every token will have those
many number of
columns. Uh so every token has these
many number of columns which are equal
to the vocabulary size.
This is called as the logit
stensor. So if we just have one batch,
the size of this logit stensor will be
four multiplied by the vocabulary size.
If we have two batches, it will be 2
mult* 4 multiplied by vocabulary size.
Don't worry about multiple batches for
now because we are just looking at one
batch currently. So every effort moves
you. Let's say these are the four tokens
and we have the number of columns equal
to my vocabulary size. Now this is
exactly what is done in the code, right?
So here we have come out of the multiple
transformer blocks. What is done here is
that if you see lnf it is another layer
of normalization. So we apply the
normalization layer here. That is what
is given in the
um if you see the output block. Yeah the
we have one more layer of normalization
here right that's the first layer of
normalization. And then if you see what
is done here is selflm head. Now this LM
head if you see that's a neural network
with the input of number of embeddings
and the output is equal to my vocabulary
size right now. So that's my neural
network with the number of rows equal to
n embedding and the number of uh columns
which is equal to my vocabulary
size. All right good. So this is the lm
head which is the output head now which
my
u which is the final output of my
transformer block. So this is my logits
matrix and this logits matrix is now
going to be used for the next token
prediction task. How is my logits matrix
prediction task? If you carefully look
at the logits matrix right now every
logits matrix has size equal to the
vocabulary right. So
uh and as I told you every batch every
batch
has multiple input target prediction
tasks. So if you see this let's take
this same example right one day a
little when we come out of the entire
transformer architecture
uh when we come out of the entire
transformer architecture we have
something like this 1 day a
little and this is now 50 to 57 or my
vocabulary size let's say all of these
are now equal to my vocabulary
size All of these are now equal to my
vocabulary
size. Okay. So the way the next token is
predicted is that when one is the input,
I look at that token index which has the
highest probability. If that is equal to
40, I go to my
vocabulary and I look for token ID 40
and I see the token associated with it.
So ideally if my model is trained, the
output should be the same as the target.
Now the target when one is the input day
is the output right that's the target
but maybe token 40 corresponds to
something like random thing like
the now when one when day when I look at
day I again look at that thing with the
maximum probability the index with the
maximum probability when one day is the
input o is the output but maybe I'll get
something like
flag then oh I look at the index which
corresponds to the maximum probability
if that index is 60 maybe that
corresponds responds to something like
uh O but my target is little and when I
look at little and I look at the index
with the maximum probability maybe that
corresponds to person but ideally my
target is girl so now I have my outputs
and I have my targets and then I'll
calculate the loss function between the
output and the
target this is how the logit tensor the
logits the output logits matrix which I
get after coming out of the transformer
block this is how it is used for the
next token prediction task. So, so one
when one batch is passed, let's say one
batch is passed, right? Which is one day
a little when it comes out of all of
these three steps, when it comes out of
the input processor and output, it has
this logits and within that there are
multiple input output tasks. There are
four input output tasks which needs to
be predicted in each batch and this is
exactly how these tasks are done. So now
there are four output target pairs,
right? we find a loss function based on
all of these four and it's this loss
which eventually needs to be minimized
in my training routine. So whenever one
batch is passed there is a loss which is
an accumulation of let's say if this is
L1 this is L2 this is L3 and L4 for
every batch my loss is L1 + L2 plus L3
plus
L4 so I get my loss for all the batches
then I do the back propagation etc and
that's how the training actually
proceeds
um yeah so until now what I've shown you
is exactly how the
uh how the transformer architecture is
assembled and let's see some details in
the code right now which we might have
missed and we'll cover some of that uh
in the future or in the rest of the
modules as well. So in the forward
method now we have token embeddings,
positional embeddings, we add them
together, we apply dropout, pass them
through through the transformer block.
In each transformer block which we have
there are multiple things which are
happening and that's defined in this
block. There is a layer normalization, a
causal self attention, another layer
normalization, a feed forward neural
network. So we go through all of these
blocks. Uh we go through all of these in
the in one transformer block. And
similarly there are multiple such
transformer blocks. When our input
embeddings come out of this they are now
context embeddings. And when they come
out of the transformer block when they
go through multiple transformer blocks
we pass them through one more uh layer
normalization layer and then we pass
them through the output neural network
which is also called as the output head.
That gives us the logits matrix. The
logits matrix when we look at the logit
matrix for every row we look at that
token ID which corresponds to the next
token prediction because that has the
maximum probability and then I compare
it with my actual
targets. That's how the loss is
calculated. So when I showed this L1, L2
um when I showed this L1, L2, L3 and L4
here actually that's the cross entropy
loss which is calculated and we'll see
that in a lot more detail in uh in the
next section actually. So the next
section after this point is going to be
the loss function. So we are going to
see that in a bit of
detail. So until now you would have
understood everything in this forward
method and in this class GPT. You have
understood class GPT, class block, class
MLP and class uh causal attention. There
are just some initializations which are
done at several places in this code
which I want to explain to you. So for
example, if you see there are these
initializations which are done. So
different modules have different
trainable parameters which are kind of
initialized in slightly different
manner. So for example, if you see over
here, here is a list of all the
trainable parameters which are usually
there, right? So the token embedding
layer has trainable parameters. The
positional embedding layer has trainable
parameters. Those are initialized as a
gshian with normal distribution and
standard deviation
0.02. Then the attention block has the
query keys and the value matrix. They
are also initialized as a goshian each
of these matrices. Then the attention
block has an output projection. Remember
I said that's optional but you can keep
that on. And that's initialized in a
slightly different manner just so that
the training process becomes a bit more
optimal. We divide it uh by square root
of two into the number of transform
transformer blocks which are there. Then
this is the feed forward neural network.
Uh the first layer which goes from 768
to 4x 768. We initialize the weights as
a goshian. And the output layer which is
also the projection layer. It's called
as the projection layer. Uh that's
initialized by a gshian. But we divide
uh 0.02 by again square root of 2 into
the number of transformer blocks which
is if it's 12 then it will be square
root of 24. Then the final layer
normalization again that has
no no initializations. and the final
output head which gets me my logits
matrix that is initialized with a gshian
of mean zero and standard deviation of
0.02. Now whenever now when you run this
code cell when you run this whole code
cell ultimately we are going to only use
class GPT which is my model and for that
we have to define a GPT configuration.
So the configuration which we are going
to use is vocabulary size of 50257.
Um then I'm going to use a block
size block size of 128 the embedding
dimensions of around 384. Um that's the
embedding size which we are going to
use and uh the dropout rate of 0.1. So
number of layers and number of heads
there is a distinction between these.
Number of layers is the number of
transformer blocks which I have. So
remember here I told you that
transformer a number of transformers
will be uh added here. So here we have
to decide the number of transformers and
that's equal to six. So here I'll just
mention
uh n layer equal to number of
transformers. Okay number of transformer
blocks and n heads is the number of
attention heads in each block.
So we did not talk about attention heads
today. But essentially when multi head
attention is computed. There are
multiple attention heads each computing
a separate attention score so that we
can capture multiple perspectives and
that's equal to six. So you can think of
this fact that in each transformer block
there is a multiate attention and the
number of attention blocks which we have
are now equal to
six. And here also we have six
transformer blocks. Right? So let me
replace this with actually six since we
have six transformer. So six transformer
blocks each have six attention heads. So
overall there will be 36 attention
heads. So this is the configuration the
n embedding is the embedding dimension
which we have right. So at the start I
told you that we have to decide an
embedding dimension. That embedding
dimension is now going to be 384. Okay.
So this is the embedding dimension which
is there. Um and then I just define my
model as GPT. So this GPT which is
mentioned here is the GPT class which we
have defined over here. My GPT class
um this GPT class which takes my input
embedding matrix and produces um a loss
which is based on the logit's output and
my target
outputs. So this is the model GPT and I
have to specify this configuration as
has been mentioned over here. Now what I
I'm going to do is that in the next
section I'm going to talk a bit more
about the loss because that's very
important to understand. In this section
four, the section four was the most
important section where we had to
understand the different steps of how
essentially the input the input uh
sequence goes through the entire
transformer architecture. the input the
processor and the output and at the
output we get this logits we get this
logits matrix and that can be used for
next token prediction task and compare
with the target next tokens and that's
how the loss function is
determined this is the whole workflow of
how the LLM architecture operates and I
hope you have understood how it maps
exactly to the code I really encourage
you to take a look at the code in in
much more detail after going through
this lecture but I've given you enough
starting point so that you'll understand
many different things which are
happening in the code. Now what we'll do
is that we'll come to the next step
which is defining the loss function. It
is very important for us to understand
what exactly happens in the small
language model loss function because
here is where we'll ultimately try to
tell the language model that look you're
making a mistake and you need to improve
upon this. Right? We have already looked
a bit at the loss in the previous part
where we saw that once the logits matrix
is obtained. Let's say here we get the
logits matrix. Right? After this point,
we look at every token and we look at
the token ID which corresponds to the
highest probability and we decode the
output corresponding to that token ID.
We compare it with the target and that's
how we get the loss
function. But now we are going to look
at this same step in a bit more detail
so that you can get an exact clarity of
what exactly is happening in the loss
function. So let's say we have the
batches which look something like this,
right? So this is my first batch and
let's say that these four tokens are my
input X1 and these are my target which
is equal to Y1. Okay. So what we'll
first do is that we'll first take X1
which is this and we'll pass it through
the transformer model. We'll pass it
through the input the processor and the
output. So let me bring this over here
so that
um you recollect what we have seen in
the previous lecture. So let me copy
paste this and u I'll bring it over
here. Okay. So what we are going to do
is that we have this input text right
which is I had always thought. I had
always thought we'll pass it through
first the input layer then it will go
through the transformer block and then
when it comes out of the transformer
block we essentially have this logits
matrix and try to think about the
uh try to think about the size of this
logits matrix right? If you have four if
you have four tokens which go as an
input they are first converted into an
embedding dimension of let's say 768
which we had seen before but once they
come out of the transformer block the
logits essentially look something like
this we still have these four tokens I
had always thought but now the
dimensions of each of them are
50257 which can be the vocabulary size
or whatever vocabulary size we have. So
if you take a look over here, this is
what we have seen previously also the
size or the dimensions of every token
are now equal to the vocabulary size.
That's the first step which is uh which
is done to calculate the loss. Then what
we do after this point here is that
essentially we want to convert every
row. So let's say this is row number
one. Uh let's say this is row number
two. This is my row number three. And
let's say this is my row number four. I
want to convert every row into a vector
of probabilities which means that I want
every element I want each row to sum up
to one. So if I consider all the
elements of row one and I sum them up I
want their summation to be one so that I
can give a probabilistic meaning to
every
token. To do that what I do is I apply
the softmax to this logits matrix and
then essentially I get a vector of
probabilities. Remember what softmax
essentially does is that it replaces
every element with let's say e to x
which is that element multiplied by e to
x1 plus e to x2 etc for a particular
row. So it ensures that all the elements
lie within 0 to 1 and they sum to one.
So now every row can be interpreted in a
probabilistic sense. So you can look at
every row and try to find that token ID
token index which has the maximum
probability. So that will be the decoded
next token. So for example, if this
token ID has the maximum probability and
if this is token ID 35, that might
correspond to a
decoded subword of AC. So we go back to
the vocabulary. Now we look at that
token ID and get the decoded token. Of
course, this is my LLM output and this
is not the target output at all. The
target output which I want
is had always thought jack. So this is
my x1 and this is my y1 right. So this
is my target
output. So for these inputs ideally I
want the target output as had always
thought jack. Okay. And if I go to my
vocabulary I see that had has a token ID
of 23. Always has a token ID of 3881.
Thought has a token ID of 11223. And
Jack has a token ID of 15. So now let me
go to this uh vector matrix of
probabilities and let me write this here
again. I had always
thought and let's look at I first okay
let's look at I first this is that 50257
[Music]
uh dimensional vector and the maximum
probability currently is at index number
35 let's say or let's say index number
35 is here that's the maximum
probability and it corresponds to the
token output of AC and what I want is
that I want the next token to be had
when I is the input So I want the token
ID corresponding to 23 to have the
maximum probability. So what I want is
that I want a token ID let's say which
is this. I want this 23 to have the
maximum probability. So ideally what I
want to do is that I want to make sure
that for the token ID number 23 which is
this this probability is as close to one
as possible. What that will ensure is
that if this probability is as close to
one, all others will be zero and my next
token which is predicted would be
had. So ideally the loss function which
I have that is constructed only based on
this token index which is 23. So
currently let's say the token index 23
has a probability of around 0.1. Let's
say in the current version let's say
token index number 23 has a probability
of.1 which is not very good. I want this
probability to be as close to one as
possible and that's how I will define my
loss. I will look at the index which I
actually want as the next token and I
will make sure that the probability
corresponding corresponding to that
index is as close to one as possible.
Let's do this exercise for the second
row which is had. Now and let me write
down the
u vocabulary size
length vector now for had. Okay, let's
say this is the vector and I want to now
look at always because when I had is the
input, I want always to be the output.
So I want the token ID corresponding to
3881 to have the maximum probability. So
here I'm going to look at the token ID
corresponding to
3881 and I will look at its probability
and currently let's say the probability
is 02 which is not good. I want to take
this probability as close to one as
possible. So I'll define the loss
between these
two. So if you notice carefully what is
going on, we have these target indexes,
right? Which play a very important role
in getting my loss function. These are
my target token ids and ultimately the
loss function will be calculated based
on these token ids itself. And I want
the probabilities which is associated
with these token ids to be as close to
one as possible.
So what we do in the next step is that
we get the output probability for the
target token ids. Which means that in
the first row we look at token number or
id number 23 and get the current
probability. Let's say that is 0.1. In
the token uh in the second token had we
look at index number 3881 and get the
probability corresponding to that. Let's
say that's 02. Similarly we get the
probabilities corresponding to always
whose true answer is thought and thought
whose true answer is Jack.
Okay. And we get these probabilities and
they are P1, P2, P3 and P4. P1, P2, P3
and P4 are probabilities corresponding
to these target token ids. And remember,
we want these probabilities to be as
close to one as possible. That's the
main uh that's the main output which we
are chasing. And the loss function which
we are going to define is exactly based
on this concept that we want all of
these probabilities to be as close to
one as possible. And so we conduct or
and so we construct a loss which is
called as the cross entropy loss which
is based on the loss fun which is based
on the logarithm. So we take the
logarithm of all of this and apply
negative sign here. Since we want to
maximize all of these probabilities when
we take the negative sign of here
essentially we want to minimize these
quantities as much as possible.
Okay. And since the probabilities always
lie between 0 and one, these this entire
quantity will be minimum when P1 is as
close to one as possible, P2 is as close
to one as possible, P3 is as close to
one as possible and P4 is as close to
one as possible. This loss which is the
negative of the summation of the
logarithms of these probabilities is
also called as the negative log
likelihood or it's also referred to as
the cross entropy loss. The cross
entropy loss is the main loss through
which we are going to do back
propagation for language models. And
it's very important for you to visualize
how we obtain this loss. Okay. First we
go through this entire transformer block
the the input the processor and the
output. When we come out of the output
block of the transformer we have this
logits matrix right from this logits
matrix essentially we have the tokens
and we have the token ids uh which
correspond to the decoded next token. So
what we do is that we have the inputs
and we have the targets. So for every
input we have a set of target token ids.
Let's say for this input I had always I
had always thought the set of target
token ids was had always thought jack
that's 23 388 1 2 3 and 15. We want the
probabilities corresponding to these
token ids to be as close to one as
possible because that will be the
decoded next token. So in the first row
I want the 23rd token to have the
highest probability. In the second row I
want the 3881 token to have the highest
probability. In the third row, I want
the 1 22 23 token to have the highest
probability. And in the fourth row, I
want the 15th token to have the highest
probability. And these probabilities are
currently P1, P2, P3, and P4. I want P1,
P2, P3, P4 to be as close to one as
possible. So I want to maximize P1 + P2
plus P3 plus P4. One more way to rewrite
this same loss is if you want to
minimize the average of log P1 plus log
P2 plus log P3 plus log P4. Taking a
logarithm is generally much more better
because if you want to maximize P1, P2,
P3 and P4, you would construct your
probability which you want to maximize
as P1 into P2 into P3 into P4. Right? Um
and taking derivatives of products is
not very easy. So you convert this into
a summation by taking a logarithm of
this and taking a derivative of this
quantity during back propagation is just
easier and we apply negative sign
because it's common notation to say that
uh loss needs to be reduced. So ideally
we want to reduce this quantity as much
as possible so that P1 P2 P3 and P4 will
be as close to one as possible and
that's the negative log likelihood loss.
What I showed you right now is just for
a single input, right? But when you are
processing an entire batch together,
what usually happens is that this logits
matrix for multiple batches are
aggregated together and the target token
ids for multiple batches or inputs of
the same batch are aggregated together.
For example, if you look at one batch
now, it has four inputs, right? X1, X2,
X3 and X4. If the batch size is equal to
four, these four inputs are aggregated
together. Their logits are aggregated
together and their target token ids are
also aggregated together. And so here we
have P1, P2, P3 and P4. Right? So then
we'll have 16 such probabilities which
we'll need to maximize because now there
are four inputs and there are four
outputs. Uh so let me repeat this once
more. Let's say if you have x1 which is
1 11 15 and 23 you have x2 which is
again these four you have x3 which is
these four and you have x4 which is
these four that's my first batch correct
and you have y1 y2 y3 and
y4 the what ideally you have is that you
have this logits matrix for x1 which is
now 4 by vocap
size you have logic logs for x2 which is
four by vocap size. You have logits for
x3 and you have logits for x4 which is
the same size. So it actually looks
something like
this. This same vector you the same
matrix you can imagine but now repeated
four
times. This is for the second this is
for the third and this is for the
fourth. Then what you do is that you
collect all of these logits matrices
together. That's called as the
flattening operation. You flatten all of
these together into one big logits
matrix right and that will essentially
now be so if you have four four such
ones right so that will be 16 multiplied
by my vocap
size so you have 16 rows over here and
this target right my target now my
target will also
be 1 2 3 4 that's corresponding to uh
y1 then I will have 1 2 3 4 that's
corresponding to Y2 1 2 3 4
corresponding to Y3 and 1 2 3 4
corresponding to Y4. Okay. And as we saw
for each Y we have four probabilities
right? P1 P2 P3 P4. So now we have P1 P2
P3 P4 that's for Y1 then P5 P6 P7 P8
that's for my Y2. Then P9, P10, P11, P12
for Y3 and
P13, P14, P15 and P16. That's for my Y4.
Now this is my set of probabilities and
I want to make all these probabilities
as close to one as possible. So we'll
just again calculate a negative like log
likelihood for this entire batch. So
that's how one batch is processed. Okay.
So when we see the code you will see
some terms such as flatten etc. So
whenever this flatten is used it
essentially makes it means that my
multiple uh inputs are now merged
together into one big uh matrix or
tensor. So that's how the loss of the
small language model is actually
calculated and you'll see that when you
have this GPT class right when you have
the class GPT the loss is actually
calculated within this class itself. If
you look at the forward method until now
we have the logits matrix right. So here
you see what is happening we have the
cross entropy loss again between the
logits and between the targets. So this
is that cross entropy loss which I
mentioned um over here. Essentially that
cross entropy loss just means taking the
negative log likelihood for the
estimated tokens which we have. And then
we have one more function which is
called as the estimate loss. This
estimate loss function essentially uh
what it does is that it gets one batch
and then it estimates the uh losses for
that entire batch actually. So here you
can see that uh for a prescribed number
of iterations let's say we have 100 uh
we have 100 iterations right and and
evaluations are done after every 100
iterations. So what happens is that for
every iteration we get one batch and
then u essentially for every batch which
we have we get the uh we get the loss
and that's added to my losses right now.
Okay. And then you see this out dot
outsplit equal to losses dot mean. So
for all of these iterations I
essentially will take a mean of mean of
the losses.
So this estimate loss what it does is
that I have to run the model for a
prescribed uh I have to run the model
for prescribed number of iterations and
uh when I when I do that when I run the
model let's say for 100 iterations for
each iteration I'm getting a different
batch when I get a batch for an
iteration let's say x and y I get a
batch which is like what I've shown here
we get a batch for an iteration we pass
this batch through the model we pass
this batch through this entire model we
get the logits. We merge all of these
logits together and then we get the loss
which has been mentioned over here. We
get the loss the cross entropy loss
that's the loss from one batch during
one iteration. When we are doing another
iteration a separate batch is is given
to us. Remember the get a batch function
sources the inputs and the targets
randomly. So if you remember what we had
seen in get a batch there is this equal
to torch.random integer right? So it
takes batch batches randomly from the
data set and once we have one batch we
can propagate it through the model and
we can get the loss. That's what's
happening here. Okay. Uh we collect all
of the losses which are happening
through different iterations. And then
what we do is that we essentially take
the
mean. We take the mean. So let's say in
the iteration number one the loss on the
batch is this. Iteration number two the
loss on the batch is this. Iteration
number three, the loss on the passive
batch is this. For all of these
iterations, the loss, the overall loss
is the mean over let's say these 100
iterations
uh the 100 iterations which we have. So
that's the estimate loss function. This
function will be very useful for us when
we are let's say training the model and
we want to print out the loss after
every evaluation iterations. So if you
want to print out the loss after every
100 iterations, it it takes the mean of
all of those 100 iterations and prints
out the and prints out the mean loss for
those 100. That's what is happening in
this loss function calculation. So this
is how we get the loss in a language
model. We convert the data set into
batches. One batch is plucked out that
that's passed through
the that's passed through my model. then
I get the loss out of uh the target
probabilities and my output
probabilities for the entire batch and
then I go to the next iteration etc.
That's how the losses are estimated.
Okay. So until now what we have done is
we have finished step number five which
is defining and calculating the language
model loss function and then we now go
to step number six which is coming to
the training loop of the small language
model. So until now let's do a quick
recap of what we have until now. What we
can do is that we can take a batch.
Let's say this is my first batch of
input X1 which has let's say X1, X2, X3
and X4. And that's my first batch of
output Y1 which is Y1, Y2, Y3 and Y4. I
can take my whole batch. I can pass it
through the language model which
consists of input, processor and output.
Then I get these logits.
then I have a loss function estimation
and I get my loss. So essentially now we
can do one full forward pass through my
input and once we can do this full
forward pass once we get the loss then
the only thing which needs to be done is
that we need to propagate this loss
backwards through my entire architecture
so that we can then update the
parameters of my architecture and that's
when we start defining the training loop
okay of the small language model. Now,
as I mentioned at the start of this
tutorial, this is going to be a bit of a
production level tutorial because we are
going to do a bit more advanced things
so that our iterations run faster. One
such advanced thing which you will
notice in the code is that we use
something like
torch.cast. The reason this is done is
that it enables something which is
called as automatic mixed precision. So
precision corresponds to float 32, float
16 etc. Um so usually by default let's
say if everything is in float 32 that
takes the longest time to compute. When
we use automatic mix precision the model
converts these to float 16 so that the
computations become faster. Now when are
the numbers converted to float 16. Let's
say if we are doing something like
matrix multiplications in the attention
score calculation or we are doing a
dropout let's say then the automatic
mixed precision would use something like
a float 16 because it's safer to compute
in lower precision over here but let's
say if we are doing soft max where
exponential operations are involved
cross entropy loss where where
logarithms are involved weight updates
etc all of these which have some
sensitive operations and which can lead
to a blow up of numbers if due to
exponential ial or log operations there
it's better to go with float
32. So in these operations we usually go
ahead with float 32 but for operations
such as matrix multiplications dropout
etc float 16 is also completely fine to
use and this automatic mixed precision
helps us do that. So wherever possible
the model uses float 16 and uh if not
then the model sticks to float 32. So
you'll see this in the code. So when we
go to step number six which is the
training configuration you'll see that
here this is where we are using the
[Music]
torch.cast. So this is important to
understand exactly why we are uh why we
are doing this uh um
torch.cast. Then the second thing which
is important to understand is that there
is something which is called as the
gradient accumulation. Okay. Now when we
go to the actual code, let's say we want
to train with a batch size of
1024. Um the problem is that
1024 input and output pairs will not fit
in my GPU at one time. If only if my GPU
can only accept let's say 32 samples. So
what we can do is that we can set
gradient accumulation steps equal to
32. So what that means is that we'll run
32 iterations. Um and then we'll update
the parameters essentially after every
steps. Instead of updating the
parameters after every 1024 steps, what
we do is that the parameters are updated
after 32 steps. So we can run 32
iterations because the b the GPU fits
only batch size of 32 and then we do it
uh then we do it once more, right? Um so
essentially we are not doing the
parameter update after every 1024 steps
but we do the parameter updates after 32
steps. This is done just so that if we
are doing the parameter updates let's
say after 1024 steps it means we'll have
to compute the gradients of batch size
equal to 1024 and we'll need to store
all those gradients but that is not
possible to do um that is not possible
to do in a GPU. If my GPU fits less
number of uh samples then we can only
calculate those many gradients and then
we can essentially update the
parameters. So here what I'll do is that
let's say uh you do first forward pass.
Let's say you do the this entire forward
pass then you calculate the gradient.
You do the forward pass once more. You
calculate the gradients like this. You
do it for 32 times right? So there will
be 32 gradients which which have
accumulated. Then what you do is that
the final gradient which is there you
then take the mean you then you then
take the you update the parameters based
on that final gradient. So you don't
update the parameters after every
gradient. So think about what happens
right in every step here one batch is
processed. So in the first step one
batch comes here x1 and y1 we do the
forward pass. In the next step the
second the second batch is the second
batch is obtained which is x2 y2.
Similarly, we do this until let's say
gradient accumulation step is 32. We do
this 32 times and until now remember we
have not updated the parameters. The
parameters will be updated only after 32
steps are done and then I go to the next
etc. So although there are 1024 batches,
the parameter updates are not done after
1024 batches. They are done after 32
batches.
Um so one more thing
uh okay one more thing I want to mention
is that gradient accumulation is
typically done if the batch sizes are
quite large okay so if the batch size is
equal to 1024 that's quite large right
because in every batch which you have x1
will have 1024 x2 will have 1024
etc and ideally the practice is to
process one entire batch and then update
the parameters but that's not what's
done over here. If the batch is used
then only 32 are done. The parameters
are updated. Then we go to the next the
parameters are updated
etc.
Um okay so let me clarify this once more
because I know that this part is a bit
tricky. So I want to mention that let's
say uh let me do this once more. Let's
say this is my one batch. Okay. And my
one batch now has 1024 such samples. And
this is my x1 and this is my
y1. Okay. What gradient accumulation
actually does is that we first go
through this
first. It's it's gone through the entire
model. Then we update uh then we get the
loss function. Then we uh get the
gradients. Okay. Then we go through the
second. We get the loss function. We get
the gradients. Similarly, we go to 32.
This is the gradient accumulation steps.
And until then, we have got all the
gradients. Once we have reached until
32, that's when we update the loss
function or rather that's when we update
my parameters. Okay. So, the parameter
update is done after these gradient
accumulation steps, not after I go
through the entire batch. That's what uh
is the main point of gradient
accumulation. And you'll see gradient
accumulation in the code also. So if you
see here gradient accumulation steps
equal to 32 right so you're accumulating
gradients up till that point and then
you are updating the parameters
essentially that's the second thing
which is important to note in this uh
training loop. The third thing which is
very important to note is how we are
doing the training process itself. Okay.
So uh when we are doing the training
process there are optimizers which need
to be used and in this case we are going
to use the Adam optimizer. uh with
weight decay. So if you scroll down over
here, you'll see that we are using the
Adam MW optimizer that just better so
that we don't get stuck in a local
minima and then training becomes stable.
But one more thing which you will see in
the code is that we use a learning rate
which looks something like this. The
learning rate warms up in a linear
manner and then it decays in sort of
like a cosine manner. So the learning
rate is a combination of a warm up plus
a decay regime that is used again for
stabilizing the training. you'll see
that we have a learning a linear a
linear function for the warm-up and then
a cosine decay. So that's my learning
rate which I'm going to use with my uh
optimizer. Generally this is seen to
have the best uh performance when
training language models such as this.
So we are using this optimization
routine. And then finally what we are
going to do is that we are going to use
the Adam MW optimizer which I mentioned.
Now all of these steps are mentioned in
step number six and step number seven. I
already mentioned the autocast to you.
So that is done the gradient
accumulation step. Uh and this is the
learning
rate. Learning rate a linear regime plus
cosine regime followed with adm
optimizer. One more crucial thing to
note here is that these are the
hyperparameters which actually I would
encourage you to explore around a bit
after I share this code file with you
and note some of the things which which
are there. We are using a batch size
essentially of 1
32. Um and uh so batch size which we the
batch size which we are using is 32 and
the gradient accumulation steps is equal
to the batch size. So in this case my
update will be done after every batch
size. But if you choose to have a larger
batch size you can stick with gradient
accumulation steps of 32. My block size
is equal to 128. Remember that's my
context size. If you go over to the
earlier
uh over here when you create the input
output pairs the block size is equal to
my context size. We have seen that in
the earlier part of this video. Um then
the batch size and block size are done
the evaluation iterations which means
I'm going to print out my losses after
every 500 iterations. Remember here what
we did if the evaluation iterations are
500 in each iteration we are getting a
batch and we are getting its losses
right so this is essentially done for uh
uh this is done for 500 iterations and
then I take the mean of all those
iterations and I'm then then I'm going
to report the
loss then what else is the
hyperparameter we have the learning rate
minimum learning rate 5 into 10 minus 4
the warm-up steps these are the
hyperparameters in the in my learning
rate routine and my learning rate 1 into
so 10 to -4 essentially and the number
of iterations which I have that's going
to be equal to 20,000 all of these are
hyperparameters and you can feel free to
play around with this as you explore
more with this
code now once you define all of these
hyperparameters and once you have
understood the different things such as
uh automatic mixed precision gradient
accumulation and uh the learning rate
warm-up plus DK then we can go ahead to
pre-train the small language model. This
is the last step in the pre-training
part and you'll see that this is the
pre-training code. So what exactly
happens in the pre-training is that u
there are 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 and eight steps
which happen and I think now you are
fully equipped to understand all these
eight steps. For each iteration we have
to choose an X and a Y. What this means
is that for each
iteration what we have to do is that we
have to essentially go through we have
to go through my data set and remember
there is this torch rand. What this does
is that this will essentially
choose random indexes from my data set
and that will give me my input pair. So
let's say this is the first index,
second, third and fourth. If the batch
size is four, this will be x1, x2, x3
and x4. And uh my y1, y2, y3 and y4 will
be these y1, y2, y3 and y4 just shifted
to the right hand side by one. So that's
the first step which is getting the
batch. So I get my batch. Then what I do
is I pass my entire batch through the
model to get the logits. This is the
forward pass which we we had seen. We
take a batch, we pass it through the
entire uh language model and we get this
logits. Once we have the logits matrix,
then we calculate the loss between the
logits and my
targets. That's my loss function. So
that I calculate in my step number step
number three. Then what I do is we do
the back propagation. Correct? We are
going to do the back
propagation which I showed through this
arrow. So that is the back propagation.
And here what we are going to do is that
we are going to accumulate the gradients
till we reach gradient accumulation
number of steps. So essentially we are
going to do this gradient accumulation
is equal to 32. We are going to
accumulate the gradients for uh we are
going to accumulate the gradients for 32
steps. So essentially for 32 iterations
we are going to
uh accumulate the gradient and uh then
what we are going to do is that once we
accumulate the gradient for 32 steps
then and only then we are going to
update the parameters. So let's say we
do one step we do back propagation. We
are not going to update the gradients.
Then we'll do one more uh iteration.
We'll again do the back propagation. One
more iteration. Again do the back
propagation. And then after we are done
through 32 steps, then we are going to
update the parameters which we have. And
once the how are the parameters updated?
The parameters are updated through the
AdamW optimizer which we have chosen. So
the simplest vanilla version of the
gradient descent looks something like
this. Minus alpha* this. Right? The adam
is a bit more complex. It takes into
account the history of the curvature
which we have in our loss landscape and
it also uses a um adaptive learning
rate. So once the parameters are updated
then we also update the learning rate
and then again we evaluate the model
after every eval iterations which is
after every 100 iterations and this loop
is repeated. So we do the forward pass.
Once we do the forward pass we back
propagate the loss. Remember that
uh remember that we are essentially
accumulating uh we are accumulating the
gradients till we reach the gradient
accumulation number of steps and only
after that point we are going to update
the parameters. The parameters are
updated through the AdamW optimizer and
then we update my learning rate. My
learning rate is updated every time the
parameters are updated because we have
an adaptive learning rate in this case.
And then what we do is that after my
learning rate is updated I when I go
through evaluation iterations which in
this case let's say if it's 100
iterations let's see how much it is the
evaluation iterations which we have is
500. So when I do 500 iterations I'm
going to evaluate my loss which is the
mean overall this 500 iterations and I'm
going to uh I'm going to print out my
loss. Okay. So that's the main thing
which is uh happening in these eight
steps. So if you see the pre-training
loop for the small language model, you
can start with this thing where we get
the batch, we get the X and Y, we pass
the X and Y to the GPU, then as the next
step, what we are doing is we pass the X
and Y through the model, we get the
logits and we get the loss. We divide
the loss with the gradient accumulation
steps because remember we are going to
update the parameters only after we
accumulate these many steps. So just so
that so the loss will also get
accumulated right over these many
gradient steps. So I'm going to just if
I have 32 steps I'm going to divide the
loss by 32 and then I'm going to do the
backward pass. Here the parameters will
be updated only after the gradient. Uh
so here I'm going to do the backward
pass. The parameters are not yet
updated. Here the parameters are
updated. So scalar.step optimizer
parameters are updated only after I
reach the gradient accumulation number
of steps. Uh then my learning rate is
also my learning rate is also updated.
Um and then this whole thing basically
uh repeats in a loop right and here what
is happening is that once we have
reached the eval iterations we are going
to print out the losses using the
estimate loss function which we saw over
here this estimate loss function. So as
you see now many things for us are
coming together when we are pre-training
the large language model right we take
the batch we pass it through the
language model we get the output that's
what's happening until this stage
uh then what we do is we do the batch
propagation and we start accumulating
the gradients but remember that we are
not
uh um we are not updating the parameters
yet only when we reach the gradient
accumulation steps we update the
parameters then we change the learning
rate And essentially this process
continues and once we have 100
evaluation 100 iterations which are 500
iterations rather which are done we call
the estimate loss function and we print
out the training loss. We print out the
validation loss and we store the
training and the validation loss. Here
what we are also doing is that we are
going to save our model which is
performing the best in this best models
parameters. PT so that we don't have to
retrain again. Remember this is also
very important. Sometimes we forget to
store the model parameters, right? And
that's not usually a good thing. The
good practice is to whenever you're
training a model, just save the
parameters because training is a very
intensive computationally intensive
procedure, right? And you don't want to
be running the loop again and again. So
we are going to save all the model
parameters which ultimately result at
the end of uh or which give the best
loss. So the best validation loss will
be associated with a certain set of
parameters. I'm going to store all of
those parameters essentially. Okay. And
uh so that I can reload the model
anytime in the future when it is needed.
So this is my training loop. You can run
this training loop now. So once you
start running this training loop, here
is where the main iterations will start.
And let me now explain to you how these
iterations usually proceed. All right.
So I hope all of you are excited to
reach this stage because here is where
the whole running of the loop actually
happens and this is the best part of
this tutorial. Until now you have spent
around two two and a half hours to go
through the entire content so far and
I've tried my best to explain every
single part of um this code as much as
possible. So first I started
with data set then data prep-processing
assembling the model architecture
setting up the training pipeline
pre-training the language model. So now
here what I've done is that I've chosen
the runtime to be 800. So on a run how
many iterations? I've run 20,000
iterations over here and it took me
around 30 to 35 minutes to run all of
these iterations. As I've mentioned to
you earlier you can even run these
iterations on a T4 GPU. That's the free
GPU.
Um, but that will take around 6 to 8
hours I think. And laptop crashes
sometimes. I've also tested with that.
So if you look at the training loss and
the validation loss, you see that the
training loss continuously goes down.
The validation loss is also continuously
going down. That's a great sign that our
training is proceeding very nicely. And
towards the end we have the training
loss to be very low. Validation loss to
be very low. And more importantly, the
training and the validation loss are
very close to each other. that indicates
that we are not overfitting over here. I
very strongly think that if you run this
for 40,000 iterations, you might even
get better results. But here I'm
sticking with just those number of
iterations which are computationally
feasible for everyone once you run these
iterations. So finally I've got a
training loss of 2.3919 and validation
loss of 2.3918. You can plot these and
here you can see that both of them
smoothly start going down. If we are
doing overfitting then what usually
happens is that the training loss
continues to goes down but the
validation loss shoots up which is
clearly not happening in our case. This
is a beautiful graph which shows that
the training and validation loss are
proceeding smoothly. So at this part we
have successfully run a small language
model on our machine and we all should
be incredibly proud of it. This is a
model which has around 15 to I think
needs to be estimated but 15 to around
30 million parameters. So still it's
definitely a small language model and
it's probably around thousand times or
10,000 times lesser number of parameters
than GPT3, GPT4 etc. But the real test
of this model is how well are we able to
do in terms of generating new content
rate. So remember we started this uh
lecture with saying that we want to uh
we want to make a model which can
essentially give
um produce coherent text. Our model
needs to produce coherent text. So it
essentially needs to produce English
stories uh which sound like a story
right uh so that will be truly awesome
because then it means that our model our
model has learned the English language
it has also learned how to form stories
etc. So what I've done after this point
which is also going to be the last step
in our uh video today that is
essentially running the inference. In
the inference, what we are going to
simply do is that we take the uh
whenever the input is passed, it goes
through the trained model. Now,
similarly, we have the logits matrix. We
get the index of the highest value. We
get the next token ID that's decoded
back to text. We produce the next token.
We append to the previous input. That
again goes into the
model. And then this loop essentially
continues. So let's say if you have
certain input like this, what happens is
that this input goes through my
model. Okay, the input goes through my
model and then I have uh my model is
fully trained now. So parameters don't
update. Then I have the decoded token
over here. My decoded token that decoded
token is appended to the input now. So
now my input at the next iteration
becomes something like this with the
appended decoded token. it goes to my
model and then again my model produces a
new decoded token which is again
appended to the input. So this process
continues until we have to prescribe how
many new words we have to generate. So
if you see in chat GPT this is exactly
what is happening right. Let's take the
same example which we took yesterday or
in the previous part of this lecture
make a travel plan for Italy. I believe
we had taken this example. So here you
see first the first token is generated
then that will be again appended to the
input then the second token is generated
that will be again appended to the input
third token is generated etc. That's how
the inference process actually happens
in language model tasks we append tokens
then a new token is decoded that's again
appended to the input that again passes
through the model new token is decoded
that's again appended to the input etc
and this process actually continues. So
this is the whole inference
pipeline. Uh this step-by-step process
enables the model to generate text
sequentially building coherent phrases
from the initial input context. So what
we are going to do now in this part of
the code is that I have uh first what I
have done is that I have stored the
model. Uh let me see where that
is. Yeah, actually my model is already
the parameters are already stored in
best model params.pt PT which is the
best which is stored in a variable
called best model params path. So what I
have done here is that I'm getting this
path over here which is best model
params path and I'm loading the model
here. So the reason I'm showing this
part of the code is that even if you
turn off your uh kernel or if you
restart your instance since this path
still contains the best parameters you
can load your entire model using this
function called load state dict. This is
so useful and you will thank me for
sharing this because sometimes or many
times it has happened with me also that
I've trained a model but forgot to save
the parameters. But it's a very simple
thing right you just store all the learn
parameters in this best model params and
then you just load it whenever it is
needed. So here I'm using load state
dick that loads the entire model
parameters into the
model and then what I'm doing is that
I'm starting with a sentence that's my
input sentence. Now uh I will encode the
input sentence and then I will call this
model dot generate. So if you see if you
scroll above my GPT class which has been
defined over here my GPT class also has
a function which is called as generate.
What this generate function does is that
it actually the same logic which I
mentioned over here. It applies this
same logic right. So first what it will
do is that it will generate this logit
tensor. Okay. then it will get the next
id based on the highest index of the uh
last row of the logit tensor that then
it will append the id to the current ids
and then this whole process will repeat
in the loop that's exactly what I
mentioned over here right uh we have the
token ID which is the input token ID
uh uh sorry we have the let me write
this whole loop over here actually we
have the current input sequence
right and in my case the input sequence
let's say something like
uh one day a little one day a little
that input sequence is passed through my
model that input sequence is passed
through my model and then I get my logit
tensor now remember the logit tensor is
one day a little and each of them is a
50 or vocabulary size vector right now
since during the inference stage we
actually don't care about these first
three at all because we just have to
know what comes after little. So we only
look at the last row over here and we
look at the token ID corresponding to
the maximum probability that's my
decoded next token if that is girl
that's appended again and then this
whole appended sequence now goes through
the model once more that's how this loop
actually proceeds. So if you see what we
do initially is that we pass this
uh yeah we get the we get the logits now
and here you see f dots
softmax logit. So then we get the vector
of probabilities and then we get the
next id based on the last row of this
probability and that is then appended to
my current uh to my current ids.
So this is exactly uh this is exactly
what happens in the generation part. And
you might be wondering what is this top
k over here. So top k essentially means
that right now we are looking at my
whole set of probabilities right and
then I'm looking at that token with the
hash probability. Top k just restricts
to let's say we look at the maximum five
tokens etc and then we choose from these
five tokens. So these are some inference
strategies which are used. There are
some other strategies also which is
called as temperature scaling. So you'll
see one more factor here which is
temperature. So that temperature
effectively controls the creativity of
my output. The higher the temperature in
the soft max every token will have
higher entropy. So it is more likely
that sometimes some token will come up
sometimes some other token will come up
etc.
Um and in the top K what is done here is
that instead of distributing the
probability among all the tokens we
essentially look at only the top tokens
and uh we are going to look at those top
tokens and select the next token from
among those top K
um from among those top K
tokens. Okay. And for that we use this
function which is called torch.topk. So
you can search about this torch.topk.
top k and it returns the k largest
elements of the given input tensor along
the given
dimension. Um okay so that's how this
generation is done the next token
generation. So you'll see that here
towards the end I pass my input sequence
through this model generate and here
it's 200. So what are these 200 over
here? So this 200 are how many new
tokens I want to generate. So if you see
over here
uh if you see over here there is this
max new tokens right. So essentially
this loop continues for how many new
tokens we are generating. So this entire
loop continues for how many new tokens
we want to generate. So I have said here
that the maximum number of new tokens
which I want to generate is 200. And
then I can just print out my output. So
the input was once upon a time there was
a pumpkin and let's see what I have got
as the output. It was very special. The
pumpkin was very happy. The pumpkin were
very happy. One day a kind lady came to
the store to you. The delicious corn
helped the world play games alone. She
had two laser soldiers who lived in the
forest. The lady felt ashamed. Her
friend said, "Don't worry, I need a
board." Now, first, what I'm amazed at
looking at this is that this story is
not there anywhere in the data set.
Okay, that's the first thing we know.
Second thing, the grammar of the
sentences looks mostly correct. The
meaning does not look quite correct and
that's probably fine. When we increase
the number of iterations, I believe
we'll get to a stage where the stories
will even be coherent. But this is still
awesome, right? It could have printed
literally anything out there. But now
our model has learned something about
the model has learned something about
the language. The model has learned
something about how to generate stories.
So you can see that the model is kind of
making sense, right? The witch said, "So
there is a witch in this story. I found
it under the garden. It's important to
help others. We need to be careful. The
lady smiled and felt happy on herself.
All right. So although you can see that
all the sentences exactly don't quite
merge together, but within just 15 to 20
million parameters, we have got the
model to a stage where it generating
something which is coherent. It's not
random tokens. It's not random words.
It's trying to generate a story that
once upon a time there was a pumpkin. It
was very special. The pumpkin were very
happy, etc. That's incredible in my
opinion because we assembled this huge
architecture. We assembled this huge
architecture and we never told anything
to the model about language or grammar
or anything. We just trained the model
to predict the next token. And due to
this training, the model has come up
with a story on its own which is not
present in the data set at all. And this
story definitely needs to improve
further. And I think it can be because
this loss can further go down. The
training and validation losses are both
going down. So I encourage all of you to
run for more iterations and you can tell
me what's the kind of stories which you
are obtaining. What's the output which
you are
obtaining. I did one more example. A
little girl went to the woods. So the
model completed it like a little girl
went to the woods and she found a basket
for her. In one he enjoyed the great
basket and the tasty treats doll. Then
she decided to go home and the picnic.
As they walked the little girl was
getting tired and didn't want to drink.
She opened her pocket to her room and
got out. This is good, right? So, it
kind of makes sense. Little girl went to
the woods, bought a basket, then she
walked back home. She got tired, didn't
want to
drink. Uh, so something is starting to
make sense. Although everything is not
making sense. So, we have literally
constructed a language model out of
nothing today and built it fully from
scratch. And this is a language model
which does not have billions and
billions of parameters. It has
parameters around 15, 20, 30 million
parameters I think. Now one more thing
which you can do once you have access to
this code is that you can apply it to
any application which you want right you
can apply it to construct an SLM for
healthcare
applications where you can let's say
develop a model which answers questions
about chat diabetes patients etc but
just make sure that the data set is
small the data set is constricted the
reason the small language model works so
well in our case is because the data set
is small the data set is around 2
million rows and it's restricted to
stories for 3 to four year olds. That's
what makes construction of the small
language model possible. So when you get
access to this code now you can apply to
so many sectors. You can apply to the
healthcare sector to create a chatbot.
You can create you can apply it in the
automotive sector where your uh language
model answers questions about cars.
Let's say you can build a language model
therapist, a small language model
therapist on your own which when you
when you interact with it, it replies
with uh answers like a therapist would.
But let's say if you're building this,
right, the data set which you have
should not be all over the internet
because then your model will need to be
huge. You need to intelligently
construct a data set which let's say
would be the most useful to a therapist.
Uh similar to how we did for the present
study. So now this kind of this video
and this notebook which I'll share with
you opens the door to you to do all
kinds of experiments. But first what you
should do is that if you have free tire
of Google Collab just use that free
tire. But if you have access to 800 GPU
that will significantly improve your
life because it's 10 to 20 times faster
than the T4 GPU. Right? So I would
highly recommend going for this. just go
for this and then run this full code and
second of all run it for 30,000 40,000
50,000 iterations. It might take two to
three hours on A100 but I think it will
be worth it because I think you will
start to get awesome stories once you
run for those many number of iterations.
I have run for 60,000 iterations and the
stories are much more better than what
I'm showing you right now. So this is a
fully functional small language model
which we have built from
scratch and we went through these seven
steps sequentially together. We started
with the data set. Then we did the
tokenization. We created input output
pairs. We assembled the entire model
architecture. Um, and the model
architecture looks essentially something
like this what I've shown over here. And
once we assemble the entire model
architecture, we set up the training
pipeline. Uh, we pre-train the LLM. We
set up things such as gradient
accumulation steps and adaptive learning
rate. Then earlier in the code we have
done some things to improve the
performance such as saving the data or
saving the token ids to a bin file for
so that and we store it in a disk for
easy retrieval. Then we have
essentially yeah done something like
x.pin memory y.pin memory etc. So that
we lock the memory of a tensor in RAM
for a faster transfer of tensor to GPU.
After this we have also done some things
such as
torch.cast which is automatic mixed
precision so that we can automatically
use float 16 wherever it's safe so that
the computational speed is increased and
we are much more efficient. So all of
these things we have done to improve the
production quality of this application.
This is not just a toy project. You can
take this code and you can augment it to
make it more industry ready. And the
last thing which we did in today's
tutorial is to run inference and show
you the quality of the stories which can
be generated. Again at the end of this
video I want to especially thank Andre
Karpati and the nano GPD repository
which he had which inspired a lot of
sections over here. many of the
architecture sections, many of
the these uh efficiency based
calculations Andre talks about a lot in
his video also and even these
calculations later which we have done
with respect to gradient accumulation
steps. Um I've been inspired a lot from
him uh as a whole. Thanks a lot
everyone. I hope you took a lot out of
this tutorial. I'll be posting many such
deep dive workshops which is 2 to three
hour workshops which are not toy
projects but which are real projects
which you can use and build on top of
this to convert these projects into
research publications. You can add those
to your profile and that will make you a
truly strong ML and large language model
engineer. Thanks so much and I look
forward to seeing you in one of these
next workshops.